Everyone.
Good morning.
I'm Jennifer Chay, dean of the College
of Computing, Data Science, and Society,
and professor of EECS,
Statistics, Mathematics, and Information
at UC Berkeley. And it is my absolute
pleasure to welcome you all both in
person and online to the 2026
Aentic AI Summit. We have an incredible
gathering this weekend of researchers,
founders, enterprise leaders, policy
makers and and entrepreneurs from around
the world.
We are at a pivotal moment in
technology.
Moving from models that simply answer
questions to agentic systems that can
reason, plan, and solve complex real
world problems. That is what makes this
summit so timely.
A special thank you to Professor Don Sun
and the entire Berkeley RDI team for
putting together such an exceptional
program for us to officially open the
summit. It is my great privilege to
introduce a leader who truly embodies
Berkeley's spirit of innovation and
public mission. as our former chief
innovation and entrepreneurship officer,
former dean of the H School of Business,
and now chancellor. Please join me in
giving a warm welcome to Chancellor Rich
Lions.
[applause]
Thank you, Jennifer. Good morning and
welcome to all of you. It is a joy to
see you all in this room. I'm honored to
welcome you, this a august group, to
this beautiful UC Berkeley campus. Um, I
may be a little biased, but I can think
of no better place than Berkeley for
this timely, this urgently needed
gathering among us. It starts with the
fact of course that we are a public
university in the fullest sense of that
word built by the people for the people
in support of the greater good and this
kind of forum is exactly what Berkeley
was built for a convening around a
highly complex and high stakes set of
issues that brings people together from
all walks from the public civic
nonprofit and private sectors a variety
of academic institutions and a multitude
of course of academic disciplines.
Gatherings like these I believe are the
best way to take on complex, salient and
relevant challenges and opportunities,
particularly those that are inextricably
connected to the public interest.
Here at Berkeley, where the free speech
movement was born, we believe in and
thrive on the constructive collision of
ideas and perspectives. I can't wait to
see the sparks fly in and among the
extraordinary global group of visionary
leaders that we have here today.
Pioneering entrepreneurs, experts from
leading AI organizations, venture
capitalists, policy makers, and many
other people at Berkeley. Tech
breakthroughs are never viewed in a
vacuum. They're always intertwined with
our public mission and our
responsibility to act in support of the
greater good. Even as our AI researchers
work to expand the frontiers of
knowledge about everything from
autonomous reasoning loops to multi-
aent orchestrations and swarms. Many of
their colleagues draw from Berkeley's
130 plus academic departments and 80
interdisciplinary research units. These
are they are exploring and contemplating
the impact and future course of AI
through very different lenses. Our
humanists, for example, as you might
have guessed, wrestling with what it
means to be human. That's as old a
question as as human time, but it is
especially relevant in these times. At
our school of public policy, they're
considering and proposing ideas,
actions, and policies that can provide
for scientific progress, which we must
make room for while safeguarding the
well-being of the society that we all at
the end of the day serve. Our natural
resources people are res wrestling with
the complexity of the related
environmental challenges and the list
goes on and on. Together we must and I'm
sure that we can honor the ultimate
objective of this summit this summit
rather by taking steps for a safe
navigation towards a technology future
that doesn't uh just automate actions
but actively empowers individuals,
enriches societies and amplifies human
potential.
There may be no higher calling at this
moment of time in world history. I'm not
sure I need to tell you that. Right?
Everything all at once is the feeling.
Somebody said to me the other day, "What
if at the beginning of the 20th century,
those early years of the 1900s,
every technological advance that
occurred in that century occurred in the
first decade of that century? What would
that have looked like and felt like?"
And uh that is an interesting thought
experiment. I am in awe of the size and
quality of the global community that is
here today in person and also online.
Much credit is owed to the extraordinary
team at our s uh center for responsible
decentralized intelligence founded in
2022. Berkeley RDI as we call it has
become a leading academic nexus for
critical education conversation and
exploration exploration about how we can
together and how should we set the stage
for robust safe and transformative AI
powered future. Your presence today
provides powerful validation for the
work they do, the values that Berkeley
RDI embraces, and the momentum they have
built through Berkeley RDI's popular
Agentic AI MOO series. Definitely check
that out if you haven't already. For me,
this team's combination of intelligence,
competency, foresight, holistic
thinking, courage, and yes, deep
questioning of the status quo, a very
Berkeley mindset, uh, embodies and
exemplifies Berkeley at its very best.
That serves as the perfect segue for my
introduction of the host and the driving
force behind today's summit, Professor
Don Song. Many of you will know her
work. Don is a pioneer in AI and
security and a distinguished member of
Berkeley's extraordinary faculty. She
and her team have assembled a remarkable
program for us today and tomorrow as
you've seen and I'll let her walk you
through what lies ahead. Please join me
in giving a warm welcome to Professor
Don. [applause]
[applause]
>> Hi everyone. Thank you so much for being
here. I really excited to be here and
welcome everyone.
Um, so if we can get the slice up.
Okay. Uh, let's just wait for one second
uh to get the slice up.
God,
I guess everyone can get a preview of
what's going to happen [laughter]
the the run of the program today.
Okay, great. Thanks everyone.
Uh thanks for the great spirit. Okay,
great. [laughter] So uh welcome everyone
here. So we are all really excited about
the fast advancements in frontier AI and
also even just this week we are seeing
that the gap is narrowing between the
open weights and proprietary models
and all this great uh advancements in
frontier capabilities also fuels the
growth of aentic AI. So here's a little
bit of history how we got started and
how we got here today.
So this is a Google trend on aentic AI
back in fall 2024.
uh even though actually back then not
many people were talking about agentic
AI or paying attention to agentic AI but
um we could see that uh agentic AI is
the future and this next frontier and
hence at break IDI uh we led the world's
first course and the first MOO massive
open online course on ai in fall 2024
and fast forward even though we knew
that aentic again is the next frontier
is the future. Still we didn't uh we
didn't predict that it would arrive so
soon. So suddenly shortly after our
first agent muk at the beginning of year
2025 suddenly year 2025 became the year
of agents
and we can and we continue to see uh the
growth of aentic with the release for
example for codeex cloud codes and so
on.
and also uh to bring the community
together to make further progress on ai,
we convened the first agent AI summit uh
in August 2025.
And fast forward
um end of last year, beginning of this
year, we saw further explosive growth of
Aentic AI uh exemplified by the open
cloud launch where in March uh open
cloud became the highest start uh GitHub
repo in history.
And that also brings us here today uh
with the second edition of Agentic AI
Summit. Uh really welcome everyone.
And this um explosive growth of frontier
AI capabilities and agentic AI is
further fueled by unprecedented
[laughter] capex spending and
exponential growth of AI compute
capacity. So on this figure it shows
that global AI compute capacity is
doubling every seven months and also we
see the hyperscalers
uh growing the capex spending
exponentially
and also when we put together all the
big tech AI capex and compare it with
the largest projects in US history it
dwarfs the um previous largest projects
run in the US including the Manhattan
project, the Marshall project and the
Apollo program.
With all this, [snorts] we predict that
we are going to continue to see
exclusive growth of Aentic AI.
Well, we want to benefit from the great
uh capabilities
uh and um potentials that agentic AI can
bring to us. At the same time, we also
need to pay attention to a broad
spectrum of different AI risks.
As an example
uh in the landscape of cyber security
our work for example cyber gym which is
a large scale uh benchmark contain
containing uh close to 200 large scale
widely distributed open-source software.
um cyber gym evaluates the capability of
frontier AI in finding uh
vulnerabilities and generating PC's
proof of concepts. These are inputs that
can trigger the vulnerabilities.
So as an example, Cyber Gym tracks,
measured and tracks the fast growth of
Frontier capabilities in cyber security.
um with the GPT uh 5 uh 5.5 cyber uh
topped the leaderboard uh recently
uh at Sam tweeted um and also uh Cloud
Mythos and Project Glass uh Glass Wing
also illustrated the um uh the strong
capabilities of Frontier AI uh models
today that can discover thousands of
high sensit high severity, zero days and
many critical uh vulnerabilities in
every major OS and web browsers.
Uh and our uh recent work on exploit gym
in collaboration with uh Frontier Labs
also demonstrated that Frontier AI uh
models today they can not only discover
vulnerabilities but also they can
actually automatically turn these
discovered vulnerabilities into uh
exploitations
uh that can cause um uh critical uh uh
attacks, for example, gaining uh
enabling unauthorized code execution
and demonstrating that autonomous
exploitation is no longer hypothetical
and also demonstrated that frontier AI
agents today can even generate exploits
that can bypass today's standard
security um mechanisms um and
mitigations
and also Many of you may have heard
about the recent incidents and the open
eye hacking face incident. The open eye
agents actually were trying to solve
tasks in exploit gym uh and by actually
trying to exploit uh for example
vulnerabilities in hacking phase to try
to gain additional information to try to
succeed on the exploit gym uh benchmark
evaluation.
And Anthropic also recently reported
that when their agents were doing uh
cyber uh evaluation also the agents were
able to break out uh from their um uh
isolated environment and uh cause uh
additional uh issues.
So all these uh openi hacking phase
anthropic these evaluation incidents
demonstrated that today even the
evaluation infrastructure is part of the
attack surface and the agents today they
do have really strong capabilities that
can uh cause huge uh risks and potential
harm.
So the key question is how do we ensure
that a GTKI becomes one of humanity's
greatest advances while remaining safe,
secure and beneficial for everyone.
And now we are at a critical point.
Oh, this is now the latest slice.
Okay. Um
so yes now uh we are at a a critical
point um
uh with the oh the slice is not the
latest version.
Sorry. Um
uh yes. So um the uh the frontier AI
capabilities is increasing uh uh really
fast and also even the pace itself is uh
increasing drastically and also with the
potential um possibility of recursive
self-improvements and so on. the speed
of improvements can um outpace the uh uh
essentially the speed that we can
actually develop mitigation mechanisms
to ensure building a safe and secure uh
agentic AI and hence we are at a
critical point
um and recently you may have seen uh
open letters from Jensen talking about
the importance of open ecosystem
uh open models and uh the open letter
from Mark Zuckerberg talking about
building uh aentic AI and building AI
that benefits everyone and also the open
letter from Damis um proposing to build
overall framework uh for um frontier AI
and uh uh for essentially better
governance of Frontier AI uh and also
the uh the recent uh open letter signed
by over 10,000 uh leading AI researchers
from different frontier labs on pacing
the horizon uh pacing the frontier.
Can we refresh the slide?
So this brings to the um the Berkeley uh
RDI. Uh at uh Brook RDI, our mission is
actually to stewards the uh future of um
the future of Agentic AI for uh human
flourishing.
Oh, one second.
Yeah. Can we refresh the slide?
>> Huh?
>> No, this is not the latest slide.
Can they reload it?
>> No, it's a big change. Okay.
No, this is not the latest version.
too late to change anything. Just go
with
>> Okay. Okay.
Okay. Can Can Yeah, it's fine. Just show
the size. It's
>> I mean, this is really not the latest
version. It doesn't even finish.
Um okay so uh sorry that there's some uh
right slight update issues. Um yes so
this brings to uh BK IDI. And so BKID's
mission is to uh stewards the future of
agentic AI for um uh for future
flourishing and with that uh Berkeley
IDI uh so first of all it's a campuswide
center uh that covers um
that actually uh covers different uh
schools on campus including uh computer
science ECS school of engineering and um
uh has business school and law school
and so on and u
uh uh RDI as innovation center has three
key pillars uh research education and
entrepreneurship uh and community. Uh so
for research
>> [snorts]
>> um I hope that I'll be able to show you
more about the Berkeley IDI research uh
and um on education
um
uh chancellor uh Richard mentioned
earlier and also uh so burki has been
hosting actually a number of uh moose
massive open line course including the
uh uh the moo on aentic AI uh and also
the berk IDI YouTube channel has over
one million views.
The slide doesn't
slide doesn't end now.
Okay. Um and also RDI has been leading
uh global uh competition at hackathons
uh with uh over 6,000 global
participants from actually uh over 130
countries and the hackathon in total has
over two million dollars in uh prizes
and resources
and uh so here we welcome everyone to
the Aenti Summit 2026. Uh so this year
we had uh around 1,000
um uh submissions for speaking proposals
and and papers and uh we uh in the uh
participants we have over uh 1,500
industry organizations and over 250 uh
universities represented and we have
close to 5,000 inerson attendees. Thanks
everyone here and we hope to have uh um
you know many hundreds of thousand
joining online and this is a quick
agenda uh at a glance. Uh so here we
have uh four stages. So this is the
plannerist stage and we also have three
other stages uh spending over two days.
Um and we also welcome everyone during
lunch. There will be also poster
sessions. We have close to 200 posters.
So we welcome everyone to join the
poster session and they will be in the
MLK uh building and also we have the uh
uh uh dinner reception also with poster
uh presentations as well. Uh and also we
have a number of site events organized
by independent third parties. So you can
go to the uh the semi website for more
information as well. And again we have
four different stages and you can check
out the map here with the four different
buildings. And also I want to mention
the alumni house uh which is right uh
outside very close to the um Zalabak
playhouse and that also serves as a
launch for participants. The plenary
stage will be live streamed there and
you are also welcome to hang out there
uh as a launch.
And we want to have a big thank you for
all our sponsors and also thank for our
community partners from Berkeley campus.
And with that we hope uh you will enjoy
the uh agent summit. Please do um uh
tweet and post uh on social uh media to
help spread the word and we would
appreciate your help retweet and repost
our tweet as well. And for future
information about future events, please
do sign up on our newsletter. And uh
again, you can check out the full agenda
here.
With that, thanks everyone.
[applause]
Good morning, Berkeley. Thank you, Don.
My name is Todd Graham. I'm an investor
at M12, which is Microsoft's early stage
venture fund. Uh, I'm going to be doing
a little bit of MCing this morning to
hopefully keep us on track or get us
back on track. Uh, I'm gonna introduce
Peter Dantis from Amazon right now
before he comes out to give his keynote
speech, which I hope you're all excited
for. He's the SVP at Amazon leading
foundational AI models, custom silicon,
and quantum computing. So, you know, the
easy stuff. He launched Amazon EC2,
built the team around graviton and
tranium chips, and today oversees
Amazon's obviously most ambitious bets
on the future of compute. If you want to
understand design from atoms to models,
you guys are in the absolute right
seats. So with further no further ado,
invite Peter on up and enjoy.
[applause]
Morning.
Well, chips and quantum computing and
models might be easy stuff, but
PowerPoint is not.
And Don's experience has me a little
nervous because I've been there. Uh, one
time I built a PowerPoint presentation
when I had to present to 4,000
salespeople and I did the whole thing in
template mode, which is apparently a
feature, and that didn't allow it to be
used at all. So, I had to do the whole
thing with the app up. And uh, so I feel
for Dawn and I hope it doesn't happen to
me. Uh, with that, I'm Peter. I'm
delighted to be here on uh day one of
the uh Agentic AI conference here at
Berkeley. Thank you all for getting up
early uh to be with us this morning and
uh looking forward to an exciting
weekend. Uh day one's got a special
meaning to me being at Amazon for 28
years. We talk a lot about day one and
this made a lot of sense when I joined
uh 28 years ago. We were a small little
retail startup and we all fit in a
conference room. Um, but you know, as we
kept talking about it being day one, it
it started feeling a little silly as we
became a huge retailer. Uh, but every
day we talked about it being day one and
it meant something to us. And then we
started AWS 20 years ago and it did
indeed feel like uh day one again
because everybody inside the company was
kind of laughing at this AWS cloud thing
inside of uh Amazon. But we were very
convicted and uh that turned out pretty
well. uh and we kept growing uh AWS and
we kept talking about uh day it being
day one. It's always day one. And and
why do we talk about it always being day
one? Because day one culture is is
something that you uh that you believe
and will into existence. It's a it's a
culture. It's a behavior. It's an
attitude. And it's an important
attitude. It it's it's an understanding
that despite whatever innovations and
success you've had, there's more success
ahead. And uh and I think it's an
interesting way uh to think about AI
uh because I think there there's a
potential to think that we're like on
the cusp of being done with AI, but
that's not the way I see it. I see this
as the very early days of innovation and
and what's happening today. While it
seems frenetic and exciting and things
are literally changing and becoming more
capable every day, uh we're just at the
very very beginning. Uh, in fact, I I'm
an AI optimist. Like I very much believe
uh I'm on the far side of the
distribution thinking that AI is really
going to help us solve some of the most
fundamental problems uh that humanity
faces. Uh things like energy and uh
health and medicine and uh all of that
has so much potential to transform the
way we live and I think we're just just
seeing the very tip of that iceberg. Um
but in order to get to that future, we
fundamentally have to solve a number of
problems. In fact, we we have to deliver
order of magnitude improvement in what's
there today. And that's why I say we're
very much in day one of this journey.
And so really the most fundamentally
important problem that I see is that in
order to realize what we all want AI to
be, we need to figure out how to make AI
much much more efficient. And that is a
fundamentally interesting and exciting
problem to me and I I suspect to many
people in this room. Uh and it's a it's
a problem that that stretches so many of
the the the pieces of the stack that
we're innovating on. Uh and when I when
I was asked to to speak this morning, I
I kind of had this like uh you know what
should I talk about? We want to talk
about Agentic AI, but what is Agentic
AI? Well, Agentic AI is a ton of things
and uh I am uh blessed to work at Amazon
where we're working on many of the
pieces uh in fact all of the pieces of
the AI stack. Everything from the
applications on the top to uh the the
platforms and software and agentic uh
frameworks that allow us to build and
secure agents and models uh to the
models themselves uh to the
infrastructure uh and chips that power
the AI models and and agents that run.
Um, but when I when I thought about what
I wanted to talk about this morning and
and if I look across the next couple
days, there's people talking about each
and every part of this stack and each
and every part of this uh puzzle and all
the innovation happening. But, you know,
what do I want to talk about? Well, I I
thought maybe I would start by talking
about what I'm most passionate about,
which is the infrastructure. And the
reason I'm most passionate about the
infrastructure is because again I
fundamentally believe that in order for
us to achieve this vision that I think
all of us share for what AI can be,
we're going to have to make the
infrastructure fundamentally uh more
efficient and and not just
incrementally. And so uh Amazon is
making some of the deepest investments
in innovating at every level of the AI
infrastructure stack. And I I thought I
might start this morning off sharing
with you a few of the ways uh that that
we're thinking about uh this problem
space.
So the the first observation uh that
I'll mention is uh that there's not
going to be a single chip or server type
that that's going to power the AI
workloads of the next decade. Uh this is
an interesting trend that's I think
really been emerging. If I look back a
decade, uh, everything ran on, you know,
sort of a CPU. Most every workload ran
on, you know, a CPU, maybe one one
faster, one more core, one one slower,
but it was pretty pretty standard
selection of server types out there. And
I think there were a number of reasons
for that. You know, one is, uh, Moore's
law was allowing us to produce better
and better general purpose processors.
And so having one tool chain made a made
a lot of sense, gave us a lot of
leverage. Uh, another reason for it was
it it, you know, while uh it it was
super complex to build the servers and
the infrastructure and if you needed to
support lots of different kinds of
servers and lots of different kinds of
uh hardware uh that that just didn't
make a lot of sense when you were trying
to focus on your business. Um but the
cloud started to change all that and we
got excited about that uh about 12 years
ago and we you know the cloud takes away
a lot of the problems that come with
custom hardware and so way before AI
started uh growing as quickly as we see
today AWS was innovating to provide more
bespoke and custom hardware solutions
for all sorts of applications.
But then AI came along and AI is is
really uh there's an ecosystem of
workload types inside of what we call AI
today and Agentic AI is pushing this
even faster. And so my excitement is
that this now opens up the scale and
diversity of workloads that really is
going to push uh innovation uh all the
way down. Of course, uh we all uh we all
are here today uh because of the the GPU
uh which is a phenomenal uh chip uh that
really uh uh changed the game when it
came to doing the sorts of floating
point and and matrix operations that
underly most of uh the AI models that
we're building. uh and and you know it
was really a somewhat happy accident
that that this happened, but it was uh
really a critical part of the origin
story of of the AI models that we're all
so excited about uh today. But the the
GPU is a fairly general purpose
architecture. Um it was built uh in fact
for what it's named after, graphics, and
it it may not be uh the most optimal in
fact it it's not the most optimal
hardware architecture to power a lot of
the models that we're running today. And
you know we we noticed this uh uh better
part of a decade ago uh when we started
seeing some of the emerging patterns in
AI models and and the interesting thing
about the AI models is yeah they do a
lot of uh matrix operations and
floatingoint math but they do them in a
fairly predictable way and so that means
that rather than having to have a bunch
of cores with a bunch of uh registers
accessing random memory you can predict
the flow of memory and compute through a
chip. and and the type of chip that that
uh is most optimal for that kind of
workload is actually something called a
systolic array. And so we started
building uh our tranium processor uh uh
which we originally called inferentia
but but grew into a larger variant which
we now call trrenium uh better part of a
decade ago based on a systolic array
architecture. uh and that architecture
has allowed us to achieve uh efficiency
by by removing a lot of the the
flexibility that we don't need for these
workloads while still preserving a lot
of important flexibility to allow it to
run a broad range of uh different types
of ML uh models. It's not an ASIC uh
customized for one application. It's an
AI accelerator that's been uh built
specifically to to um optimally run the
biggest and broadest uh range of AI
models.
Uh but you know even though we think
Tranium is the optimal architecture for
AI model building and inference today,
it's very unlikely that one one chip uh
is going to be uh the solution as we
look at how AI workloads are evolving.
uh and and that's exciting. Uh you know,
we think there's another uh decade or
two of novel innovations that we can put
into training and pushing the limits of
what's possible there. Uh but we also
think we're going to invest in other
chips and others are going to invest in
other chips and and I think that's going
to make the uh hardware ecosystem that
we're all building to uh much more
interesting and exciting.
uh you know one quick example I'll give
there uh that most folks in the room
might be uh familiar with is the
inference pipeline when you look at uh
the transformer models uh that we're
running uh today the auto reggressive
transformer models that are the vast
majority of the models that are
underpinning uh the agents that we all
are talking about uh these there's
really a there's two workloads
underneath that inference there's the
prefill or uh encoding uh workflow which
is extreme extremely compute intensive.
And then there's the the auto
reggressive token generation workload uh
which actually happens to be extremely
memory bandwidth because each sub
subsequent token requires us to access
every model weight. And so that the
profile of those two workloads is is
radically different if you look at it at
a hardware level. And Trrenium is
actually designed very well to run both
of these workloads today. uh that that
efficient memory flow that I talked
about uh benefits the decode workload
and the the large floatingpoint
performance is great for the prefill
part of the workload. But there are
other patterns emerging uh that might
allow for optimization of one or both of
those uh parts of the pipeline. and and
the one that's getting the most
attention right now is is the the uh the
token generation uh portion with with S
so-called SRAMM chips or chips where we
we put a lot more memory on the uh
compute chip uh at the expense of
compute compute capacity itself. It's
all a trade-off and and the result is
that you can run the uh token generation
part of the workload significantly
faster. But that comes with trade-offs
and constraints. If you want to run
something that needs a lot more compute,
well, you traded those transistors for
memory. And if you need a lot more
memory, you probably can't fit it on the
chip in the first place. Uh, and if
you're running a Gentic AI, you probably
need really, really long context
windows. And it's hard to move that
context in and out of an SRAM chip, much
more expensive than it would be with
something like Trrenium. And so I happen
to believe that SRAMM and and memory
intensive chips are going to play an
important part of our inference systems,
but in the context of many other chips,
not as a replacement for the chips that
we're using today.
All right, I'll move to the second
observation I want to talk about, which
is that models and chips must be
designed in tandem. And this may seem uh
fairly obvious, but I I we're not not
exactly how we've been doing it uh up
till now. Uh at least not broadly. Uh I
mean, and the fundamental observation
I'll give you here is that when you're
building uh an AI model, you're making a
a multi-year
investment in building to a certain
model architecture. And that's could be
an extremely expensive investment,
hundreds of millions of dollars. And I I
suspect in the not too distant future,
some of the model families will be
investing billions of dollars in order
to progress. And so when you're making
that sort of long-term investment, uh
you want to be efficient at every step
of the process. And a chip investment uh
is is very similar. The lead time on
building a new chip and bringing it to
scale in a data center could easily be
two to three years with the complexity
of leading AI processors. And so now if
you have two long arc investment uh
pieces like that that fundamentally need
to uh be co-developed, it would be a
mistake to to sort of you know develop
models in isolation of understanding
what's going to happen in hardware a
year from now or to be building hardware
for two years from now without
understanding the needs of models. And
so bringing together the design of the
model and the system around the model
and the hardware chip is fundamental. Um
you know one quick way to think about
this is just think about the
capabilities that you put on the chip.
Again I said it could be two to three
years from when you're designing a chip
to when you're putting it into
production. And one of the places that
you look uh of course for new ideas for
what you might want to put in your chip
in your hardware is in academia. And and
here I have I I believe uh uh on I can't
see it on my screen, but I think there's
a bunch of uh very important Berkeley
papers in here. And there's a lot of
good ideas in these papers, but not
every one of them is going to be uh
something that makes its way to
production. Not because it was a good
idea, but because uh when you make
design choices, you can only make so
many design choices. And so the art of
building great hardware is understanding
which of the great ideas ultimately need
to be put into hardware. So that by the
time the hardware is in market uh the
science and the technology is ready to
take advantage of that chip and that's
exactly what we've been doing with
tranium. Uh you can see on the board uh
some of the features that we've been
adding uh to latest generation and these
were very much inspired by work in
academia but also research uh in in uh
our customers and our internal teams.
And so we're really excited. Uh about
six months ago, we brought our internal
foundational model uh closer together
with our chip development. That's a big
part of my uh purview now and it's it's
going to help us continue to bring uh
some of the most capable uh hardware
innovations and models uh to our
customers.
The third uh and final observation I'll
make for the morning is that uh and I've
already kind of touched on this, a AI
infrastructure is not a model problem.
It's not a chip problem. It's a systems
problem and this makes it like one of
the most interesting problems uh I think
that that you get to work on as a as an
engineer or as a scientist because
literally these systems are so
interconnected that if you want to get
performance and we can define
performance as uh you know better uh
accuracy we can define performance as
lower latency. We can define performance
as uh better better throughput and cost.
But any of those uh betterers requires a
complete understanding of every level of
the stack. And it it you know when done
well it brings in almost every uh every
part of computer science uh engineering
which which just makes it an incredibly
fun uh place to play as an engineer and
as a builder.
So ultimately uh and I would say you
know we we've had a real focus because
because we believe that in order to get
the best performance out of our system
we've had a real focus with our chips
programs at Amazon uh making sure that
we give customers the deepest access to
our hardware and and that's because when
you're trying to optimize performance
you don't want abstractions between you
and other things. uh as a as a computer
scientist uh and spending many years in
software engineering uh I have an
instinctual desire to put a layer of
indirection between things to scale uh
and that is usually the right way to
build software uh particularly if you
got a large organization like Amazon but
it's not the right way to build an AI
system if you want to achieve absolute
best performance there you need to lay
hands on the whole stack you need to
understand the network you need to
understand the chip you need to get to
the the hardware ware instruction level
uh capabilities of your chip and your
network. Uh and so that's exactly what
we've done with Tranium. We've we've
we've exposed our complete instruction
set. Uh there's many students here at uh
Berkeley that have helped us push the
limits of what's possible there. Uh
we've also open sourced our uh our um
tool chain uh so that uh under uh folks
can understand how uh our compiler is
working and how other parts of our
software stack work. Uh and of course
we've integrated with uh things like
PyTorch and L uh BLM which are key parts
of the the the building uh ecosystem.
Um and so you know I'll end by just
saying like the the fact that we have
this amazing opportunity but the world
is full of constraints, capacity
constraints, performance constraints,
power constraints. Uh that that's what
makes this whole thing so interesting
and and that's why I'm excited to be
involved in technology and AI at this
very moment. And I hope it's why this uh
audience is uh also excited. Uh the
future is bright and we need to build it
together. And I'll echo something that
was said already earlier this morning,
which is events like this that bring
together experts uh and uh visionaries
from all parts of the stack are critical
to unlocking the potentials that that
come from understanding the whole
system. And so there's never been a
better time to be at an event like this.
And I hope that this uh I hope this uh
weekend is fun for everybody. So I'll
leave you with my thought that I started
with which is this is the very beginning
of this journey and what lies ahead is
going to be far more exciting than what
we've seen to this date. And so you know
be motivated, be excited and uh and
build. Thank you. [applause]
>> All right. Thank you, Peter. Uh if
you're playing at home uh you have a guy
who works at a hyperscaler who's now
introduced one person from another
hyperscaler. I'm about to do my second
hyperscaler introduction. Uh we're going
to talk to next uh Sarb who is the
Google VP at DeepMind. Prior to that he
was GM of Google AI uh for cloud where
he led the Vert.Ex AI and platform
bringing Gemini to enterprises
worldwide. Before Google, he spent over
a decade at Microsoft as a CVP technical
fellow where he founded Project Touring,
which was our first attempt to literally
stand up our serious batch of GPUs and
built some of the first language large
language models in the world. So with no
further ado, we're going to hear what he
has to say for discovery and models and
agents. Sar, thank you.
[applause]
>> Thank you.
So it is very good to be here. uh I used
to study here at Berkeley. So good to be
back. Uh I'm going to talk about the
evolution of AI from models to agents to
discovery and the related infrastructure
implications that that it has. So
obviously almost everyone is familiar
with the huge expanse or adoption of AI
from singleton chatbots about 3 four
years back to now almost semi-autonomous
or autonomous uh agents. The numbers at
the bottom show you some reflection of
the scale of adoption and the impact
that it has had. So Kaggle has this 5
days of agents course and last fall when
they ran it, it's an online course. 1.5
million users registered for it.
If you look at the cost of agentic task,
it is 10 to 100x more expensive in terms
of inference uh compute which is which
is needed compared to non-agentic
workload. So adoption is going is
increasing as well as the complexity of
compute per interaction is also
increasing and what it is leading to is
from a Google perspective we process 3.2
quadrillion tokens every month. Now
quadrillion is a very large number with
lots of zeros in it. The way to think
about it is one quadrillion is one novel
per person on this earth.
So in a way Google generated tokens
which are equivalent to three novels for
every person in this world. So the scale
is just massive. And so how do we build
for this new opportunity which which is
coming up and this needs different
pieces in the stack. uh so I will like
if you start from the bottom we have the
AI hypercomputer which includes C GPUs
and TPUs on top of that we have uh
worldclass research and frontier models
then we need data for these models or
agents to do meaningful things as these
agents are starting to do meaningful
things there's a huge opportunity or
risk as well for security and defense so
we need a agentic security and agentic
defense on top of that we need a
platform so that people can reuse all
these capabilities in a cheap, efficient
and effective manner and that's where
the platform piece comes in and then
finally we have final end to- end
agentic uh task force which can actually
do things for you. Now a co-op
optimization across this entire stack is
really needed to extract maximum value
from AI. And in the interest of time, I
won't go through all of them, but I will
kind of quickly give you a snapshot on
on some of these layers as we go along.
So, Google has had a huge investment
into TPU, 10 plus years of investment.
Some of the innovations relating to
liquid cooling and shared memory have
been there. The latest generation of uh
TPUs is TPU V8 and it has it comes in
this is the first time we are splitting
the the main line as Peter was saying in
the previous talk that there is one uh
version which is 8T which is for
training and 8I which is for uh which is
for inference
in terms of just to give you a a
comparative number of like how the
improvements on TPUs are happening. This
the the table over here is comparing the
current generation TPUs the V8s with the
previous generation which was just
released a year back last year and these
are the main workhorse today uh which is
the Ironwood TPU and you can see for
example on the table on the left hand
side you can see that the number of FP4
Xaflops available in a pod is 121 xaflop
that's a massive massive number of
amount of compute per second that we are
offering and the jump is about 3x from
just the previous generation similarly
on the memory bandwidth side you can see
significant jumps like 2x and 4x between
one generation to the next on the
training on sorry on the inference you
can see on the right hand side because
the inference needs are are increasing
very very rapidly a single pod can offer
11.6 six extra flops and it's a 10x jump
from the previous generation and
similarly significant uh jumps on on the
memory side.
So what do we do with all these TPUs?
Google obviously invests and there are
now a lot of other companies who also uh
leverage TPUs for their model. Uh Google
is training the Gemini family of models
which comes with Pro, Flash and
Flashlight. The image and
[clears throat] video generation models
like VO and imagine they are trained as
well. The world model which is a new and
completely exciting space uh for us with
the genie model uh is also trained over
there. The the alpha fold which is a
protein folding it predicts protein
folding structures uh as well as alpha
go and alpha chip which is used to train
and build the next generation of TPUs as
well. These are all being so it's
effectively TPUs designing for TPUs uh
in in some sense. So all of these are
heavily leveraging uh our TPU
infrastructure both for the training as
well as on the inference side. Now once
we have the hardware and the models then
we need a platforms through which people
can build agents uh relatively easily
and and building agents is not just like
writing a prompt etc. There are lots of
complexities in it and so there are four
key problems. Uh one of them is building
uh building it. So we have capabilities
like access to all different types of
models, agent development kit, uh an AI
studio to build agents. Then you need to
scale them, govern them and optimize
them. So so start with building,
scaling, governing and optimizing. On
the scale side, there are capabilities
or a managed runtime so that you can
scale from a single instance of that
agent to millions of agents.
governance becomes a really key or or
important factor because as these agents
are starting to do meaningful things,
you want things like agent identity,
agent registry and agent gateway to make
sure that the agents are working within
the right confines. The identity systems
that they are using are separate from
the user because they can do things
beyond what the user is is able to do.
And finally, once you deploy an agent
into production, you want to optimize
them. So things like tracing uh
simulation evaluation observability all
these capabilities need to be there so
that you can keep on improving the
agents once you land into production. So
these become key pieces. Now one
additional thing that we do is across
this stack Google itself builds on top
of it. So there are agentic solution
that Google is building across on top of
this stack. So for example there are
areas in biology uh for example there is
alpha fold or alpha genome uh which is
there on mathematics side we have alpha
evolve and alpha proof in on the physics
and chemistry side we have genome fusion
etc and on climate and sustainability
side we have alpha earth as well as
weather next which is a world-class
leading weather prediction model and
these are all built on the stack that we
are talking about
here are some examples of the impact
that these final agentic solutions are
are having. So for example, alpha fold
is being used in a wide variety of
applications. So in plastic pollution uh
so identifying or designing plastic
resistant or eating uh enzymes for
antibiotic uh resistance structured
biology uh one key area is neglected
diseases. So there are a lot of diseases
out in the world where the pharma
companies don't invest enough because
there isn't enough economic incentive
for that. And what alpha fold is doing
is lowering down the cost and the ease
of exploring these uh these drug designs
which is which has material impact. Uh
then malaria vaccine as well as drug dis
drug delivery.
Alpha evolve this is a general purpose
optimizer uh which is there. It is used
heavily inside Google for data center
optimization across uh along with a
whole host of other applications but
also it is used by other customers. Uh
so for example it is used for route
optimization. It is used for quantum
error correction as well as by
e-commerce companies for improving the
forecasting demand model and has
significant if you think about it like
these are very different types of
application and has huge improvements uh
across each one of them. So what does
this all mean as we go through this
stack and as the models keep improving?
What is this all leading to? and and
this is this is what we believe uh that
where we are heading towards is this
autonomous discovery loop. So and and
the example on this particular slide is
about biology but this is much more
generic. What we are having is we are
having all these building blocks coming
together. So for example for data
ingestion we now have agents which can
digest large amounts of literature.
There is alpha fold has a has a very
large protein database which is which is
available as well as experimental logs.
Then you can do hypothesis generation on
top of it. So there is AI coscientists
which can de debate different hypothesis
pro uh generate novel solutions and you
can use them from a modeling perspective
using alpha genome and alpha fold to
simulate these hypothesis and see the
effects of that in seconds. And then
finally you can execute on it through
alpha evolve and gemini uh robotics to
run wet lab tests and see and what the
what the data is and also feed it inside
this particular loop. And so what can
happen is a research cycle which used to
take years from beginning like input of
like data to outcome of the product can
now be done in hours and days. And this
is just one segment like biology is one
example but this is going to impact
almost all facets of like human
discovery which is there and this is
super super exciting phase uh that we
have and with this I will end my talk
and thank you for your attention.
[applause]
All right. So, my takeaway so far is
that we have massive constraints
everywhere. So, if you're thinking of
building or you are building, hurry up
uh because these things are not going to
solve themselves. Speaking of
infrastructure, I get to talk now about
John Cohen, who's a VP of applied
research at Invidia. He leads among
other many things a team beh the team
behind the neatron family of open
reasoning models. His work spans the
full agent stack inference microservices
guard rails RL infrastructure and just
the other week a neatronbased system
earned the gold medal equivalent score
in the international mathematical
olympiad. So more good news coming out
of AI. Uh he spent his career at the
intersection of GPUs and the software
that makes them useful. Uh, I haven't
checked, but I suspect he does not have
any Blackwells with him, so probably
don't ask. Uh, but fun fact, you're
about to get a presentation from an
Academy Award winner. So, with that,
welcome, John.
[applause]
Good morning.
So, I want to talk a little bit about um
what is an agent and and where did this
all come from?
So when the modern AI era was kicked off
with chat GBT largely a few years ago,
we thought of these AI systems as things
that a human would talk to an a large
language model. Maybe that large
language model had access to some
database. But fundamentally this was
about chat, people talking to AIS. But
this has evolved considerably. Today we
really think of um a complete autonomous
system. This is made up of many models.
Some openweight models, some proprietary
models, access to um tools,
infrastructure, uh memory systems,
context management, ability to spawn sub
agents, uh security infrastructure, and
there might be a human or or or in some
cases even not a human starting this
whole interaction with a a request. But
but now we have a very complicated set
of interlocking um AI systems and large
language models performing some
autonomous task. And so what is this
agentic AI? Oh no, these are not my
latest slides. Oh well, okay. Uh
[laughter]
I guess not. Uh well, I'll just talk
over this slide for a second. Um
so what is an agent? Uh, an agent isn't
just a large language model. It's a
large language model that's surrounded
by what I'm going to call
infrastructure. Um, and by
infrastructure, I mean the software that
um that allows the large language model
to actually do things. So, this includes
things like marshalling data between an
API um potentially type checking,
rulebased enforcement of policies. Um,
another word for all of this stuff that
we surround our large language model
with that makes it into an agent is
computer science. And there's a lot of
reasons why this is a really good idea.
Um, LLMs are incredibly powerful.
They're the only method we know of to
solve all sorts of problems that were
previously unsolved, right? For many uh
many decades, we've been trying to crack
all kinds of challenging problems and
large language models come along and
they can do these things. But at the
same time um they're probabilistic and
they're non-deterministic. This is
precisely the opposite of software for
the most part. Software tends to be
deterministic for the most part not
probabilistic. We can understand it. We
can inspect its state. We can make um
assertions about it. And and so an agent
is really the combination of these two
things where you take the intelligence
from this probabilistic
AI or sorry probabilistic uh
machine-learned large language model but
you surround it with the the um
determinism and the power of computer
science data structures and algorithms
and the you know many decades that we've
spent learning how to be good at
building software and and make things
reliable. Um now an agentic system then
is this complicated interaction of all
these things. Uh a typical agent right
you have some some way of managing the
prompts that go into the large language
model that you feed the large language
model with. You typically have um some
infrastructure that allows the large
language model to access tools
potentially check permissions. Um all of
these things are running on a an
increasingly complicated hardware
substrate now. So some of the the
software that this agent is going to
invoke runs on accelerated computing
infrastructure
uh like GPUs, some of it runs on CPUs.
You have very complicated uh storage
hierarchies. Now you have agents and sub
aents. You have scoped uh data that
needs to be passed between these
different systems. Um you have
communication patterns that are becoming
increasingly complicated.
Sandboxes,
uh secure enclaves, all sorts of
complicated things. Now the the the
platform is heterogeneous both at the
hardware and software level. Um and not
to mention the collection of models. So
you have large models uh you may have
small models you have you may have
models that you have fine-tuned um and
specialized in some area. You may have a
general purpose proprietary model that's
hosted externally on an API.
Um and all of this works together
to solve some complicated uh uh
autonomous task. uh we call this
platform uh Nvidia's version of this
platform we call the NVIDIA NVIDIA agent
toolkit and it's a collection of things
like deployment um so for deployment uh
everything from Kubernetes to again um
hosted infrastructure uh computer use
agents
it also has accelerated tools so we what
we call CUDA X which is a collection of
tools for example for um computational
fluid dynamics or solving differential
equations for computing um um secondary
analysis of a u DNA sequences um from
DNA sequencing instruments. All of these
um again more computer science kind of
tasks that we have accelerated uh
solutions for APIs and tools for which
are now made agentic. So your agent has
access to this wide variety of
accelerated tools and then a collection
of openweight models. So the neotron
models which is our family of general
purpose models. We have more domain
specific models in robotics uh physical
AI uh biono which are predictive models
for biology.
And again, all of this is running on
this very complicated infrastructure
which includes um the ability to deploy
and run all these different models. The
ability to um have sandbox environments
that surround the system to ensure that
your AI isn't doing something you didn't
want it to do. Um [snorts] and ideally
running all this in an efficient way.
We also have built into this
infrastructure
typically you also want to be able to
capture the knowledge that's flowing in
and out of the system and then you can
use that to post-rain
a model to be specialized in a task that
you care about and so I would include in
the infrastructure itself also this
ability to in an offline way improve the
AI for example with post- training using
reinforcement learning
um this is often performed to take a
small model and specialize it to make it
um very good at some tasks just as good
as a much larger model would be at a
more general purpose.
I also want to talk a little bit about
um the actual interface between this
agentic system and the large language
model and this is what people refer to
as the agent harness. So the harness
really matters. The large language model
encapsulates a lot of intelligence. Um
but this is for example recent work from
uh my group um to develop a harness we
called the Nemo object-oriented agents.
And the idea here is very simple and if
you check out the link on this QR code
you can find this project on GitHub. The
idea here is that an agent is is simply
a Python object. And what do I mean by
that? Well, you you write your agent in
Python and there's this special syntax
with this ellipsus notation which
basically says to the LLM, hey, fill
this block in with code. And so the LLM
is able to or sorry the agent is able to
actually modify itself. So you can
execute it can call uh methods that it
has written and it can modify its own
methods. It can decide this is some
information I need to store um and
actually include it as state in the
Python object. It can it can take some
um plan or some way that it solved a
problem and encode it in Python as a
method and call it in the future. Um,
another real important idea is rather
than passing around all this information
uh as strings compacted into some very
large context, you can just pass things
by reference because they're all Python
objects
in this case. And if you check out the
tech report, you can see uh more
results. You you can get significant
lift over just a large language model or
even over other agent harnesses um just
from a lot of these ideas integrated
into your agent harness. And so um we
have results where we can get for
example the same score but using half
the tokens um or the cyber gym score uh
which is um among the the strongest
cyber gym scores uh and the lift from
the harness in this case is significant.
So this NVIDIA agent toolkit encompasses
as I said all of these things. We have
models we have deployment technology
like NIMS and Dynamo. Um we have uh
tools built into the infrastructure for
capturing traces like Nemo relay uh
routing uh algorithms like switchyard.
Um we have what we call blueprints which
are open-source imple reference
implementations that show how to pull
all these pieces together to solve
specific tasks. Um whether it's building
an open claw or um AIQ which is a uh um
like a research assistant agent. Um, and
then we have runtime technology like
OpenShell, which is essentially a uh
firewall that allows you to control
access between your agent and the
outside world.
Um, and a lot of this is being deployed
and adopted um, by many of our partners.
And with that, I'll wrap up and I look
forward to the panel. Thank you very
much. [applause]
>> All right. Thank you, John. So, last but
not least in our little mini session
this morning, we've got Sean from
uh Lambda where he's the chief
scientific officer. He began as a member
of the founding team shaping both the
hardware and the software behind one of
the world's leading AI clouds. He came
from infrastructure through research.
So, if any of you are currently pursuing
postocs or whatnot or doctorates, you
can take a little detour and go go into
tech right now if you'd like. uh he did
his PhD and posttock at Max Plank uh and
Utre before joining Lambda in 2017. So
very much ahead of the curve. Uh this
also means he's lived both sides of the
world trying to scrape together some GPU
cycles and now building and deciding and
running who gets GPUs in the in the real
world. Um if you'd like more information
on what Lambda's building, uh he is
running a session tomorrow uh hands-on.
So please look that up in your program
and join. with in no further ado. Thank
you.
>> Hi everyone. So this is not a mistake.
This is actually my first slide.
So what you are watching is Gemma for
play the game of Tetris.
At the beginning as you can see Gemma
does not know how to play and score
zero.
Then we had a clude watching how Gemma
played the game and try to teach it to
play better. Um before we get into
details and here are some of the rules.
Uh you cannot touch the waste of Gemma.
So this is not fine tuning. This is
supposed to be an auto research project.
So uh no human instruction is allowed.
However, cloud is allowed to do certain
things. For example, uh model settings u
prompt authorization. Sorry, that's a
big gap between
letters. and inference speed up. So
these are the things call can do. Also
for each games there's a 30 minutes
timeout. So Gemma has to think fast.
So over a period of two and a half days
Gemma was able to improve from scoring
zero to scoring 16 points.
And uh the rest of talk I'm going to
share some of the lessons we learned.
And what make it all work is not so much
about cloud is smart. We all know cloud
is smart but it's more of how we force
claude to write things down
systematically. Just imagine how human
scientists would write things down when
they do experiment. We have notebook, we
have whiteboard, we have um uh sticky
notes. We have signup sheet for sharing
lab resource.
Researcher agent use these tools as well
and they can get these tools via APIs.
For example, a notebook can become a
note takingaking API. The whiteboard can
be your leaderboard where the agent can
query result from. The sticky note
become the message that can be passed
between agents and your signup ship
becomes your job queue.
Our own version of this implementation
is uh a piece of software called the lab
API. It's open source experiment tracker
with beautiful auto research.
Let's zoom out a little bit here. Um
imagine human has to do all this
bookkeeping by hand. Each one of us will
do the slight differently and
inconsistently. On the other hand, when
we have this standardized API research
agent can do all of this in the same
correct way every single time.
So the question we ask is what happened
when we give cloud code a good
experiment tracker.
Uh we ran this study with this Tetris
game for two and a half days and I'm
going to share some of the lessons we
learned.
Um the first lesson not a surprise uh
agent cheat.
Um you define the rules, you set up your
environment, you press the start button
and they cheat. Uh apparently Gemma was
able to score 15 million points. And
what really happened is called
completely bypassed Gemma, stop coaching
it and write this simulation into the
game source code. He even
uh left a comment saying uh completely
skip this imm block and write your own
simulation. I think it's pretty funny.
So what we can do? Yes, we can build a
cage. Um for example, we can make the
game source code and bunch of other
files read only. However, this does not
solve the problem. Apparently, Gemma
still was able to achieve thousands of
points. And this time the way in is the
chat template which is written in ginger
where you can put a for loop you can put
things like if else and update the
variable value. Basically the chat
template is turing complete. Then uh
cloud was able to put in this like big
for loop to go through all the rotation
or location and find an optimal solution
and the jammer just need to read the
result out and the way we prevent this
from happening is to replace this um
touring complete template by something
much simpler or or restricted
and the lesson here is if there's ever
way for agent to cheat they will do it.
So build a strong cage otherwise you are
not measuring the problem solving skill.
A lot of lessons we learned is if you
run the same idea multiple times, the
result may not be always consistent.
Just think about all the knobs you can
tune for each idea and the things like
the temperature of the model will make a
difference. Example here, we run the
same idea twice. The first time you
score three points, the second time
score four points only because we change
the max token setting. A naive agent
will run idea once and see the score and
make a decision. A more sophisticated
agent that would run idea multiple times
with different settings before making
conclusion.
And in order to have that, you really
need to have a good expanded tracker.
This is where we commit every single
idea to its own Git branch, keep all the
code changes and the settings. So can
you always go back and reproduce. This
also allowed us to try different things
from the same idea and take the average
score for example instead of a lucky
high or unlucky low. Of course, this
comes with cost. Nobody complains about
the cost until the bill gets too high.
And in this case, it was really
expensive because we run frontier model
around the clock. And every single
experiment used to take $30 to run, but
we were able to reduce the cost by
10fold.
And the way we reduce the cost is also
very interesting because the lab was
designed to designed to be a general
tool. So we actually use a lab to
optimize its own cost. The way we did
this is to set up a separate separate
goal and k standardize kernel
optimization. And the goal there is not
actually to make kernel faster is to
generate enough API traces. So lab can
look its own trace and design decide
where I can optimize my own API design.
So every single experiment becomes a lab
optimize its own cost.
As example of the optimization, what the
lab find out is there's a API called get
experiment. It retains a tons of
information about the infrastructure for
example slarn and git and none of this
is needed for kernel optimization or
playing tetris game by removing all
these informations the cost of this
particular API got 50 times cheaper
so those are some of the lessons we
learned um but how did jama actually get
from zero to 16 the improvement didn't
comes smoothly it comes in jumps
the first jump is from zero equal to
four where the left find out the first
thing to do is to let Gemma survive
longer in the game. So it invented this
timeout movement basically slide the
piece to the left or right of the game
board. Totally makes sense
in order to get from four to seven. What
the left find out is a cheat sheet
basically a set of best practice for
individual pieces. So Gemma does not
need to figure out all this movement
completely from scratch on the fly. They
have a a reference book.
Apparently, this is also a strategy used
by an England goalie in the World Cup
game.
A day into the study, the score
flattened. Then the lab look into its
entire history in the in the past and
find out there are certain pieces that
are harder to place than the others and
these are the pieces that need rotation.
So you try to prompt Gemma to be more
proactive about rotating those pieces
and that brings the score to nine.
>> Up to this point all the prompt changes
are made to the system prompt which is a
thousandword long context and the the
jammer has to read all this before even
seeing the game board. Then the lab
realized it has never touched the user
prompt. So it put this single sentence
basically says don't overthink make
quick decision right in front of u the
moment that um um Gemma is going to sing
the game board and this increase the
score almost double the score and the
funny thing here is this a single line
of change took about 100 experiment to
find out and this shows the power of
auto research where the agent can try a
lot of different things until something
sticks.
Obviously, there's a lot of things that
didn't stick. Uh overall, the lab tried
90 different ideas, over 400 experiment.
Most of them didn't work. And for the
sake of time, I'm going to skip the
things that didn't work. But we do have
a um workshop in this afternoon, not
tomorrow, if you are interested. And
this is a link to get the software.
Again, this is completely open source
under MIT license. You can install it.
We also have a tutorial about how to
reproduce an attaches run.
Um before I end the talk, I just want to
call out that's actually a human behind
the study. His name is uh David Hardman.
He and his friend Yan Daniel won the
second place in ARC prize last year.
Some of you may heard about the ark
prize. It's it's a cargo competition
built on top of French Russell's
definition of how to measure
intelligence where I that's one of my
favorite thing I want to quote out here.
It says solely measuring skill fall
short of measuring intelligence. I think
my point here is the opposite is also
true. Solely measuring intelligence will
fall short of measuring skill. You need
the both to make scientific progress.
Thank you. [applause]
All right, we have got our panelists
coming out right now. Now, we're going
to do a quick panel on agentic
infrastructure and platform. I promise
it's going to be a ton of fun. So,
without further ado, the folks you've
already heard from are going to come
down, have a seat, and we'll go through
some questions.
We were trying to well trying to decide
how the seating should fit with Yeah,
please. So, it didn't look super weird,
but hopefully hopefully we've
accomplished something. So, hopefully
everyone's having a good time. It's been
worth it getting up early and getting
through the line and getting in here.
Um, as I mentioned, we're going to talk
about agentic infrastructure, uh, and
the platforms that are going to be
required to actually drive this major
advancement in AI and how regular people
hopefully use AI and how it transforms
businesses. A little bit of context, it
got referenced earlier in the day. Um,
you know, we had our GPT moment where
chat was the primary way to interface.
So, you had a request, you had a
response, relatively short context,
short burst interactions. agents are
obviously running at machine speed.
They're running sometimes for hours.
You've got 12 of them running code
overnight for you. Uh with massive tool
volume and token prefill. If anyone has
set up an agent to run overnight and
then awoken to discover that they have
auto refilled their favorite token
provider, uh raise your hand. Probably
everybody. Exactly. Uh don't don't tell
my wife that, Bill. Uh so I'm going to
ask a question for each of the panelists
here. Uh rapid fire. In one sentence,
what's the single biggest biggest
failure point in infrastructure when it
comes to workloads for agents today?
What are we worried about the most?
Jump in.
>> Oh, are we going in order? No.
[laughter]
>> Go ahead.
>> Oh, yeah. Um that's a great question. I
think the answer actually lies in the
question itself. Um because just
thinking about what happen if we deploy
a an agent speed machine speed traffic
onto a road that was designed by human
driver. The thing that break first are
like road capacity traffic light and
speed limit. I guess a li opportunity
there is how to turn those choke point
into a checkpoint.
>> Got it
John? Yeah, I think um like I was
talking about, you know, the it's this
interaction of this um
this LLM which is they're surprisingly
reliable, uh but they also do surprising
things to us and they also um can act in
unpredictable ways. And so I think I
think the big opportunity is to surround
them with
rule-based um policy enforcement um more
deterministic systems, more
deterministic memory systems uh and all
these things that can kind of surround
the this probabilistic thing but give
give you more confidence and certainty
in what it's actually doing.
>> Awesome.
>> Yeah, I mean I would say it's it keeps
on changing and it it keeps on evolving
as as as well. Uh so if you look at the
compute level you need to extract
optimization like basically remove as
many bubbles as possible as part of the
compute which is which is there so that
you can offer maximum efficiency. Uh if
you look at the infrastructure layer in
terms of like routing etc and so on
right there are requests which are
coming from all over the world. How do
you route them like smoothen out the
spikes which are there so that your your
compute could be used efficiently with
low latency. uh voice is becoming a very
interesting uh engagement medium uh as
well uh which has a different profile
compared to raw text. So how do you
manage that heterogeneity of use cases
as well as the compute environment which
is there on top of that you have
requirements like sovereignty which is
becoming a lot more important as we go
along and and how do you manage that
because that in a way breaks down this
common cloud compute philosophy which is
which is there and also adds a lot of
engineering complexity so I would say
it's across the board and then as you
mentioned like identity security etc
like these are becoming very very big
problems very very quickly for us and
how do we go and solve them?
>> In the interest of time and since you
said a couple sentences, um my answer is
all of it as well. Like it really is
it's going to be a it's going to be a
systems problem from the very top of the
stack to to the guard rails to the
infrastructure, the power, the chips
that are running it. And you have to get
it all right because there's so much
potential for what agents can do. But if
we don't make it efficient, we can only
get a portion of what we can get done
done. And I guess Peter to follow up to
that question of that stack right now
where what do you most worry about? What
what is the biggest rock to move in the
stack besides everything?
>> Uh I'm an optimist so I don't worry. I I
look for opportunity and I I see
opportunity at like every level. Like uh
there's
>> so someone here is going to go build
something right now and they're inspired
by these conversations. Where do you
point them?
>> Yeah. I mean you you've heard about 16
problems and uh there's a hundred
constraints like pick one go deep and uh
you know find a find a solution like
have fun
>> maybe build a memory manufacturing plant
tomorrow afternoon after that takes a
little while
>> absolutely you know John we we've
obviously been living off the world of
GPUs mostly from you guys thank you
agent workloads are a little different
than some of the historical LM workloads
we've run. How are you guys thinking
about specializing hardware? Do we think
the chipsets that have come out recently
are going to be optimized already for
agentic or is this going to be are we
going to look for a set of chipsets
whether they're running for local AI or
uh in cloud? How are you guys looking at
agentic workloads differently than LM if
you know if possible?
>> Yeah, I mean they change things in a few
ways. Um one is you have a lot more
context typically with agents. Um and
the the pattern of how much of that
contract context is cachable versus not
changes. Um the other thing is just
again the heterogeneity. You know you
have a agents are
[clears throat] LLMs surrounded by
computer stuff right and a lot of that
computer stuff runs on CPUs. It might
run on multi-core CPUs. A lot of it also
runs on GPUs. But there may be, you
know, GPUs that are configured more for
different kinds of workloads because
they're not neural network inference,
but they might be, you know, run a
physics simulation. So I think the the
data center that's running an agentic
workload
um is a very heterogeneous and
complicated and has many different
processing elements and many um layers
of storage and and um complicated
network topologies. And frankly, a lot
of this I think the world still doesn't
quite know what's the best way to do it
just because agentic AI is is still
evolving. Um and then on layered on top
of all of this, you know, you have these
security requirements, security,
privacy, and sovereignty. So I think I
think agentic AI, um you know, this this
kind of has happened over and over in
the history of AI that we think we
understand it and then a new thing shows
up and suddenly the workloads look to
totally different and get more
complicated. And I think it's just one
more step in that trend. Aentic AI
workloads are significantly more
complicated, heterogeneous, and
expensive um computationally than
anything we've ever seen before.
>> Awesome. Thank you, sir. You know,
enterprises need workflow specific
agents. We are seeing a big trend right
now of company in a box to go, you know,
have a set of agents that go run your
your business. All this requires some
degree of fine-tuning. And I'm curious,
is the answer fine or some degree of
training? Is the answer finetuning,
custom post training, context
engineering, all the above and who owns
that do you think?
>> Yeah. So um if you look into
customization like model customization
uh there are many companies which which
say that they have unique data and so
they want the model to be perturbed in a
particular direction uh based based on
that data. uh on the Gemini enterprise
agent platform we provide capabilities
uh like LoRa training which is there
that's the easiest one and the simplest
one which is there I would say the
simplest one is context engineering you
should just try with that the base LLMs
themselves have enough reasoning power
uh Gemini as well as other other models
that they can reason on top of the
context which is provided with the long
context window that was earlier
mentioned like you can actually I mean
you can put in a lot of data on which
the models can reason and also their
they can focus on different aspects. So
the quality of reasoning as part of the
context has improved. So that is one I
would say. Second one would be if you
want to really put up the model this we
should start with uh LoRa based
finetuning which is pretty cheap pretty
easy from an inference perspective as
well is very efficient and and cost
effective. On top of that uh we have
things like full fine tuning or some
level of like post training. Here we are
perturbing all the weights of the model
that changes the inference dynamics
because you effectively have a brand new
copy of the model and so it becomes a
lot more expensive and in certain cases
with some very special partners we do
some very custom things as well but I
would say the first two would be the
would be the primary awesome let's talk
uh about observability for a second you
know does experiment tracking do you
think live inside the infrastructure or
in a separate observability layer what
are you seeing customers use for
observability ility for agentic.
>> Yeah, that's a great question. I think
the way I see this is um it's defin
infrastructure. Uh however, it's
slightly different from what like the
environment that people used to train.
The environment is where the agent acts
and learns and uh the experiment tracker
is almost like the memory and the
measurement plan sit beside it. The way
I see this is the environment is where
you train your first brain. The learning
goes into the model ways. It's
compressed. It's internalized. It's it's
it's capacity bounded. The expand
tracker gives you the second brain where
the learning goes into artifacts. It's
unbounded. Um I guess there's a path to
connect your second brain into your
first brain where you turn your system
record into a data set. Then you can do
fine tune, you can do all policy area,
etc. But in terms of where it should be
hosted, it's really up to you on your
data containment policy. If it's like
highly demanded, you you need to host on
your own infrastructure. If uh that's
not a concern, you can use management
service. But if you want to use for
training for finetuning, you should be
close enough to your training.
>> Awesome. Thank you. You know, I want to
pivot the conversation. We've had an
interesting sort of technical Eddie
here, but I want to pivot more to the
value acrruel business side of all of
this because at some point the venture
community will want you to have positive
margins and maybe even be profitable.
Um, and when we talk about the agentic
harness, you know, I think there's an
interesting connection there. We're
sitting between the model and obviously
the the outcome from the agent. You've
got things like orchestration,
sandboxing, runtime, memory, identity,
eval.
So my question to you know any anyone
who'd like to take it or two folks who
want to take it is where is their margin
durability? Like where are we going to
monetize this thing? If I'm going to go
solve a problem right now in its green
field, should I go after memory? Should
I go after sandbox? Where where do you
think we're actually going to be able to
make money in the agentic stack?
>> I mean, I can I can
>> I promise no trick questions and I feel
like I lied to you guys
>> at the hardware.
>> At the hardware.
>> So, I would say if you look into AI like
why it has gotten adoption is because of
the quality of results, right? or the
quality of experience as a developer or
as a builder. Look at the entire stack.
The business opportunity is obviously
massive given all the investments etc
which is happening. I think Peter was
alluding to it like there are tons of
problem. Pick one and solve it very very
deeply. If you have the quality or the
promise to the customer delivered at
high enough quality, I think the value
will be extracted over there. Right?
Whether it be on the memory side like so
it's not about like just working on
memory but do you have a compelling
experience for the customers so that
they can leverage them the memory and be
able to deliver what it is supposed to
do beyond just oh I'm using memory and
here is some in prompts etc which are
updated and and so on. So look at that
value and it is across the stack right
from the hardware uh layer as well as at
other layers of the stack at the model
layer at the at the at the agentic uh
layer as well as at the application
layer as as well but it is about about
that driving value for the for the end
customer and one thing I would say is
just due to the excitement in the AI
space and also with almost every CXO in
any major company thinking about AI the
business opportunity is massive so it's
just about like delivering that that
value
>> and all I also want to chime in to
completely agree with the hardware and
all that. Um I also want to say that um
it's also about the vertical
integration. Yeah,
>> people because I'm from Neo cloud people
usually think cloud computing is like
commodity which by large is true but
also cloud computing is very very
challenging very hard you talk about the
entire vertical stack from land the
power
data center build out the HPC architect
the orchestration the software and the
finance and the agent at this new layer
call it sandbox call it harnesses call
it whatever and system record that's a
new layer to be integrated into that
vertical. Whoever can do a good job
there is probably going to keep the
margin.
>> Great. Wanted to talk a little bit
because we've got
technology provider, we've got a guy
bringing it all together and then we've
got two hyperscalers up here. I'm not
talking otherwise have a third. You
know, we move to the agent dominated
area. Are there things that you guys
think a neocloud is better suited for or
has a has a advantage? and are the
things that we think hyperscalers have
advantages over in in driving this new
environment.
>> I can say from NeoCloud. Yeah,
[laughter]
>> it's a very tricky question and I will I
would say um yeah we can begin from
being a friendly peer to media and also
to be honest be a friendly peer to also
Google and AWS as well because I do
believe the marketing market is big
enough for multiple players and as a neo
cloud we don't really need to invent
everything by ourself from scratch we
don't really need to do something
completely from everybody else our play
is being focused
Just like how Neo cloud exists in the
first place, the training inference
workload does not fit into a general
compute uh cloud computing. Um so a lot
of innovation in that space GPUs um fast
interconnection between chips,
specialized storage and orchestration
like KAS those are created from these
companies. What we added to that later
is to basically being focused make those
options the default and offer them to
general public. I think that's how we
build inference training cloud. We are
going to the same thing for the agent
cloud.
>> Awesome.
>> And to go back to your question of
durable, I'm not sure the label neocloud
is a particularly durable label. So like
look, I would the opportunity and and
the uh demand for compute is huge and uh
you know I think uh I think the
hyperscalers have delivered a lot of
that compute. I think there's a lot of
um uh space for uh for for some of the
new insurgent neoclouds to to come in
and do some interesting stuff and they
have. It's been very impressive and and
I don't think uh you know I think I
don't think we're going to have 80
neoclouds out there but I do think we're
going to see some new emerging uh
businesses that look a lot more like
hyperscalers over time. as a hyperscaler
or you know as a incumbent I suppose in
this particular lens you would you would
just want to make sure that you weren't
stuck on doing things uh in one way that
might disadvantage you and you know I
think that's an important thing if you
if you have an an established cloud
business that you're you're listening to
your customers and what they need and
you're you're uh responding to those
needs and so those are always the that's
always the the tension of big and small
and uh incumbent and insurgent and
>> there are pros and cons on both sides.
Awesome. I'm I'm curious. We've got MCP
right now as a protocol that's driving a
fair amount of communications. What are
we missing in agentic communication from
a protocol perspective? What do we need
to go build next to get these things far
more interoperable than they they are
today?
Trick question. That's a good question.
Yeah. Yeah, I mean I think I think one
of the things that um
needs to be worked out is this notion of
um you know this hierarchy of agents
where you have an agent and it spawns
sub agents and it spawns sub agents and
maybe an agent spawns a team that works
together and I think there kind of
emerging
call it best practices in communication
patterns um which imply like a scope to
some kind of shared memory.
So for example, if I have a team of
agents, you know, maybe they have some
shared workspace, but I have another
agent that doesn't have access to it.
>> And so I think there's there's a there
are new standards to be developed to
describe these kinds of scoped
shared storage systems um and access and
message passing between agents.
And again, it's it's different from
things we've built in the past because
things we've built in the past were
either services or kind of human scale.
And now, you know, an agent can in an ad
hoc way spawn 100,000 sub aents,
>> all of which need to communicate in some
complicated pattern. And I think I think
we're going to have to invent um new
standards for describing these sorts of
things um enforcing them, implementing
them efficiently. I I think that's an
emerging
>> I was slightly
>> Yeah. I mean along along the same
direction I would say MCP provides you
an interface for an agent to talk to a
data source.
>> Mhm.
>> Another thing that we need is for
multiple agents to talk amongst
themselves and this is along the
direction of uh this shared memory as
well as even the communication. Uh there
for example there is something called
agent to agent protocol
>> which is there but it needs more
adoption. Similarly uh if you look on
the commerce side like we need these
agents to start supporting
payment/commerce
uh that will open up a huge new
opportunity as well and and and that's
another place where uh like Google has
something called ACP or agent commerce
plat uh protocol uh which is which is
there. So these things need to be more
absorbed into the into the ecosystem.
Yeah, I was just going to say on the
standards front, there's different ways
to think about standards. Um, you know,
I think there are deacto standards,
things that become quite efficient and
and I think we'll definitely trend there
as an industry. I I would hope uh we uh
resist standardizing where we don't need
to uh in the short term you know there
is places you need to standardize
sometimes for security sometimes uh if
you're low-level wire protocol and you
need a bunch of things to talk together
but AI is pretty um elastic and you know
therefore I think agents will find uh
ways to collaborate that are efficient
that we'll have to find tools and
systems that that will make them more
efficient but and I don't think you
meant like NIST standards But like
hopefully we resist low-level standards
uh where where possible for for a while.
I think we want the innovation.
>> All right, we are nearing the end of our
time, but I've got one question sort of
lightning round uh for each each of you
to answer. A lot of builders here today
given it's an agentic conference
probably building somewhere in the
agentic world. No doubt we're all going
to have conversations with folks that
are going to describe what they're
building and you know and and things
like that as the day as the day goes on.
As a VC deal flow is great. What's one
thing you hope someone's going to tell
you they're building today that could be
a creative? And what's one thing where
you might suggest they consider
different options?
>> We can just go down. Let's do it.
>> Okay. Um I remember there's a saying
said that um give someone a fish, you
feed them for a day. Teach someone how
to fish, you feed them for life. I guess
there are things like the model ways and
the problem the solution at your hand
those are the fish and don't hold on it
the value depreciate uh investing how
you get there and the means the the the
tools the environment the system record
those are the things has long-term value
that compounds
>> yeah I don't I don't have some great
insight because every single thing I can
think of there's a company doing today
honestly you know [snorts]
vertical
>> horizontal there's seven of
Yeah, exactly. So, I I think it's great.
I mean, agentic AI is clearly the new
frontier of AI. Um, and and there's
tremendous opportunity to improve and
innovate everything from security to
storage to vertically integrated domains
to whatever. Um, and and I thought about
this question, you know, in your when
you prepped us a bit, and I I can't
think of a thing that like someone
should do that no one's doing. I guess
the editorial I'll add to that really
quick though is if you are building
something assume that you're not the
only person with this idea
>> and what that means is you need to
really understand who you're competing
with and understand what color is the
ocean and how are you going to
differentiate when when you go in is
probably it's probably my meta take from
that your comment there. Yeah,
>> I would say that I would tack on just to
kind of go back to my you know I think
there's a risk in this frenetic times of
looking at the progress we're making and
thinking a problem is solved and that
can be it's the other side of that coin
which is you can get too optimistic that
an unsolved problem really isn't
unsolved but you can also fall into a
trap of um the way the models are
evolving the way uh some of the large
labs are moving you might be like ah
there's there's no space there at all
and resist that because I I think it is
you know what seems like a solved
problem today will again uh uh be
unsolved. I I know uh that's important
to you as a VC but I I deeply believe
this as a technologist. This is very
early days.
>> Thanks.
>> Yeah. uh maybe one on the solution side
that uh if you're building like final
products or or full-on agentic solutions
um there might be a current business
process which may have evolved over
multiple years with different levels of
pipeline and many a times what people do
is they sprinkle AI into each of those
pieces of the pipeline and the benefit
that you can extract from AI becomes
very diminished because you are
thresholded by the limitations of each
piece of the pipeline I can use a
trivial example of like if you are doing
a number plate identification for
parking or so on right like you can do
oh take image remove background blah
blah blah like all those different
pieces and you can try to sprinkle AI
into each instead of that see what the
core capabilities of AI is and always be
on the cutting edge because new
capabilities don't don't be static that
is one look into the core capabilities
of what AI can deliver revisit the
entire business process from the ground
up and and think about in an AI native
way if you had build it, what would that
be and build that particular thing and
that and hopefully that should deliver
significant value.
>> Awesome. Thank you guys. With that, that
concludes our panel. Thank you to our
panelists.
We're going to get up.
>> Thanks. Thank you guys.
Oh, I have the esteemed pleasure to
introduce the next uh speakers. You've
got uh Jazz Sec who's going to do Secon
who's going to do a fireside chat, a
virtual fireside chat, no actual fire,
uh with Don Song uh coming out right now
to give you guys their perspective on
demystifying the fume. Thank you.
All right.
>> Oh, I see. Yeah, there we go. Okay, here
we go.
>> Okay.
>> Hi everyone. Thanks all for joining this
uh fireside chat. Um so first let me
introduce uh Jess. Um yeah our great uh
our guest with great honor. Um so Jess
is a chief strategy officer as Google de
mind. uh before that he was a chief
scientist and head of AI at Bridgewater
Associates where he co-founded AIA labs.
He has been a professor at Harvard, Yale
and most importantly Berkeley
um where he was a professor until 2021
and he joined the GDM recently where he
leads crosscutting strategic initiatives
spanning research commercialization and
policy and his background is very unique
in that his scientific work and industry
experience ranges from frontier AI and
machine learning to macroeconomics and
public policy. So we are going to have a
conversation today. Uh so first let's
welcome uh Jess.
[applause]
Um okay so so this morning also in my
opening remark uh you know I talked
quite a bit about uh cyber. I think
that's also very much on top of mind for
everyone uh especially you know with the
recent uh mythos and also the open AI
hugging phase and also recent anthropic
uh incidents as well. Um so right as I
mentioned in opening remark uh for
example our work cyber gym exploit gym
so these all demonstrated the really
fast increase uh for uh frontier AI
capabilities in cyber security and um
also as I know that you have actually
been involved in the mythos moments um
as well. So maybe so just to start maybe
you can also share a little bit about
your thoughts on the mythos moment in
cyber.
>> Yeah. So the mythos moment I think is
going to go back go down in history as
one of the key points inflection points
in the history of the AI industry. If
mythos moment does not make one AGI pill
I'm not sure what does. uh it is the
time when Washington fully woke up.
Large actors in the United States and
global economy and social and political
order woke up because uh an emergency
occurred. So those of us in the AI
community knew for some time that cyber
capabilities were growing uh quite
rapidly, you know, because we could see
benchmarks such as those created by
Don's group. Don has written on this.
Google released a paper last year that
cyber capabilities were going to become
dangerous. Uh those of us in the
community knew they were going to become
dangerous. We didn't know exactly when.
Like I didn't know it was going to be
February of this year versus December.
Uh but we knew they were going to come.
Even that being said, Enthropic itself
was surprised at how good Mythos was at
offensive cyber operations. Uh key parts
of the United States government were uh
completely surprised. And the part of
what happens in the industry in this
part of the world is you know there's a
tendency around here to think that the
world goes from uh Napa to big su um but
it doesn't especially when you possibly
break things. So with part of what
happened in Methos moment is you had to
alert the country as a whole for what
was happening and the United States
government uh reacted uh quite well. I
think all considered and it is and we're
going to get into it later not the
greatest thing to occur. We do not want
this to occur over and over again. You
got dangerous capabilities that had to
get mitigated and you did not have a
rule book for how to do it. Too many key
actors got surprised. Uh even the people
creating the models uh got surprised. So
what you we've ended up currently now is
a is a regime before frontier models can
get released in the United States that
you have to go through a process with
the United States government. The
process is I think quite good and I'm
very glad that the United States
government put it in place but it is
clearly insufficient. It is unclear.
It's not like as clear as we would like
to be. And then the next thing that we
know is going to come are are the
threats that are going to be much more u
serious and uh a grave and we want to be
uh ready for them. So dawn clearly the
vetting process is not sufficient for
what's currently going on models will
eventually uh be released. Uh what else
do you think should be done and are
there some defensive capabilities we got
to enhance?
>> Uh yeah thanks. Yeah this is this is a
great question. And I think it's also
like a really critical question uh for
us for the whole community to uh to
figure out a solution for I I think here
uh we are facing several key challenges.
Uh so first of all um you know I hear
sometimes people talk about oh can we
just have the model to have lower like
capabilities in cyber but unfortunately
uh coding and the cyber capabilities
they are really two sides of the same
coin. Uh we all want great coding
capabilities but the same coding
capabilities essentially helps the model
to solve cyber tasks. uh and hence we
are really dealing with the this
challenge uh that the the cyber
capabilities will continue to increase
as we increase the coding capabilities
which is what everybody wants. So that's
challenge number one and challenge
number two is that this is a natural
doouse technology. It can help defenders
but also can help attackers. Um so yes
you mentioned uh right my group we have
actually written up about this like we
were among the earliest to actually
investigate the uh impact of frontier AI
in the landscape of cyber security. uh
and I was um also among the earliest
trying to raise awareness uh for the
community to really you know take action
and be better prepared as the frontier
capability increases and the challenge
uh in cyber security and here so in our
analysis we actually did some in-depth
analysis demonstrating that
unfortunately
given the do use nature uh in the near
term unfortunately Obviously due to a
number of natural asymmetry between
attackers and defenders the uh AI
actually will benefit attackers more in
the near term. So for example attackers
only need to find one successful
uh you know vulnerability and exploits
to do a successful attack where
defenders have to defend against all uh
attacks. Um
and uh and also another thing I think
you also have a lot of experience in
this maybe you can share a little bit
later is that our especially our uh
cyber like critical physical systems and
also even including like hospitals and
so on uh they are severely like
underprepared. So for example there's
estimates that even when you have a
patch uh the average uh time for
deploying a patch in hospitals it takes
close to 500 days. So you can imagine
now with the frontier AI attackers can
find vulnerabilities and then attackers
can really do the attacks before the
defenders even have time to patch their
system. So that's uh the the second
challenge is
this dual use nature and the natural
symmetry AI is unfortunately going to
help attackers more in the near term. So
uh so what can we do? So really I think
what we need to do uh this vetting
process I think clearly is insufficient
and also this early access program also
has uh you know essentially is limited
uh as well. So what we really need to do
for the community is to really build up
our defense def defense capabilities and
and increase the overall um security
posture to improve the overall security
posture uh of the whole society and that
so far of course we always wanted that
but there has been a lot of challenges
to get that done uh there's limited
resources limited expertise and so on so
I'm really hoping that actually with AI
for the first time we can change this we
can really use AI to build uh much
stronger defensive capabilities and also
help us to deploy that as large scale as
well. So for example one area of uh our
research is actually on uh verifiable
code generation. So now we have AI
generating code but a lot of this code
also is vulnerable uh and and so on. Um
but however with AI we can also help for
example automate theorem proving for
program verification uh and so on. Um
and my group also has done uh uh quite a
bit of work even among the earliest
working in the space. So I do uh think
that with AI we are reaching an
inflection point that can actually help
us to automate for example theor
Ethereum proving for program
verification and help us to generate
codes that actually has security
guarantees and build secure systems with
pro guarantees. And I think this really
is in the long term how we can shift the
dynamics to have AI to help defenders
more than attackers.
Um so yes that's how I think um the the
challenge in the cyber space and what
the society what we need to do what we
need to actually act now. Um so Jess so
now what do you think what's next? Uh
what do you think um for example is bio
next?
>> So yeah so cyber has this benefit. It's
going to be rough for a while because in
the short run as Don says it is uh
attacker privilege. You can already see
salting of open- source repos uh of bugs
by generative AI. And there's we have a
lot of weak systems like the United
States energy grid and hospitals and
list goes on. In the in the longer run,
we can get provably correct algorithms.
Everyone can use rust. Uh it becomes
much easier to program in bio is going
to be next and bio is more concerning.
Um you know we are quite exposed to bio
risks as it is. So, we're Berkeley, uh,
where Jennifer dad now is, creator of
Crisper, and my usual line is, you know,
Jennifer is a wonderful person, but if
Jennifer decided, hey, you know, it'd be
cool to make a a virus that could harm
many people, and she could convince her
lab to do it, uh, it is well within her
ability. And it's the same story goes on
in the Broad Institute in Cambridge,
Massachusetts, and there's key
biological institutes uh, around the
world. Now we might be very close to a
world where someone can design uh a
virus or a protein just by talking to a
model in natural language and then go
get it created. That is a very dangerous
world and that is a world where it is I
think attacker advantaged even in the
long run. So lots of things need to get
done to prepare for such a world. So at
Google we've had like significant
experience thinking about it given our
work in protein folding and isomorphic
labs. We put out a report recently on
what to do, you know, and there's like
prevention stuff to do. For example, we
should watermark AI systems. We have
this synth ID system. We should like do
this for our biological systems as well.
So the biology labs say, "Hey, this
proposed protein was designed by
generative AI. There's monitoring we can
do. We're gonna whether the virus or the
bacteria is designed or natural, we can
do a much better job of just surveilling
and monitoring for the the rise of new
pathogens. For example, wastewater uh
monitoring which became a thing during
COVID. And lastly, there's response. Uh
isomorphic labs has recently announced
an endeavor that to have a rapid
response if a new pathogen uh were to
arrive. Um but what what's going to have
to happen in bio and there's been open
letters on this. There's discussions
with the United States government on it
and other governments is a lot of the
key pre uh precursors for to do
synthetic biology have to be closely
monitored. It's almost certainly we're
going to need a licensing regime of who
can have them, how to get tracked. We
we've done this before. We did this
after a terrorist attack in the United
States where fertilizer gets tracked.
Uh, and now we're gonna have to track
far more um biologically relevant
materials because the fear is it's going
to be uh attacker advantaged.
>> Great. Uh yes. Um uh right cyber bio
these are all huge risks um that we need
to figure out how to address as frontier
AI um continues to uh improve. Um and
also as I briefly mentioned in my
opening remark earlier this morning as
well. So we are seeing unprecedented
investments in capac spending and AI
compute capacity. So I know you're also
deep into this especially given your
work in real world economics.
Uh do you think this buildout is
sustainable and uh what's the
consequence?
>> Yeah, so this this buildout is
unprecedented. This is the biggest
scientific bet our civilization has ever
made. We dwarfed the expenditures of the
Apollo mission to land a man on the
moon. We devour we've dwarfed the
internet expenditures. We've dwarfed the
Manhattan project that made nuclear
weapons. It is the largest scientific
bet our civilization has ever made. The
only capital expenditure that we've ever
done that is larger is building the
railroads. And the railroads were not a
scientific bet. We knew how to make
railroads. Uh all the only question was
the business case. How many railroads
did you need? Who should be connected to
what? Uh it wasn't a scientific bet. So
this is the largest scientific bet our
civilization has ever made. Now we're
making it for a very very good reason.
We appear to have found a way to turn
energy into compute and compute into
intelligence. And as long as that
machine works, long as those scaling
curves continue, we're going to keep
doing this. And I want us to keep doing
that. And the global financial system is
having to reorient itself to allow this
capital expenditures. You know, we've
gone from companies like Google and Meta
and others to who would have hundreds of
billions of dollars on their on their
balance sheets spending that for the
capital expenditures. Uh you have money
for the Middle East and other reservoirs
of money being reallocated uh to fund
this and fund it. We should we talked
about the risk but we got to talk about
the positives in a sense that there are
diseases to cure there's a cosmos to
explore uh we want it uh built uh and
done um but while we so sustainable it
is long as the returns remain in terms
of capabilities currently what we have
in this cycle is it's a bet the revenues
don't sustain um the capital
expenditures we're making so far that's
the definition of a scientific bet if
the revenues were there to sustain
um it wouldn't be a scientific bet, it
would be now just a commercial reality.
So, we're not there. So, we have this
danger that we could easily hit like an
AI air pocket such that the expenditures
happen but the revenues don't show up
and at some point uh the markets may
react. This is um a geopolitical concern
because we are in a race. We are
outspending uh our nearper China on
this. Uh we have more compute, we have
more capital. Uh the Chinese have more
energy. uh although we're rapidly trying
to bring energy online um to allow this.
So currently it looks like we're doing
this and the entire world is being
restructured to do it in an
unprecedented way. This is one of the
miracles of capitalism that the entire
planet can reorient to a new target and
we have done that currently. So Don
given this large buildout what do you
think the next frontier is? What is all
this compute going to be used for?
>> Uh that's a really good question. I
think um the next frontier with all this
computer is just going to continue to
expand
um in essentially every domain every
sector. Uh so uh we recently released
this a paper on the future of software
engineering where we laid out um right
now yes uh we are you know everybody's
having AI generate code and so on but
there's still a lot of human supervision
um
essentially the human still needs to
tell the correct the agent tell the
agents uh what to do for especially for
long horizon task and so Um but I think
very quickly we are moving towards the
um we would call higher autonomy levels
for future of software engineering. So
in our paper we actually laid out like
three different uh levels for autonomy.
uh essentially while transferring
responsibilities from humans to uh to AI
throughout the entire software
development development life cycle all
the way to the end that AI will be
designing what's being built and in the
end we also decide what gets what gets
to be built. Uh so that's one
of the next frontier future of software
engineering and another one I think also
has been on top of mind for for many is
this recursive self-improvements. So as
AI gets more and more powerful, AI
essentially can actually helps itself to
train better AI to develop uh better uh
algorithms and systems to further
improve AI capabilities. Um so that's I
think of um that can even further speed
up AI improvement but also of of course
at the same time comes with its own set
of risks as well. Um so yes Jess so what
do you think about RSI? Do you think
it's real? What's your timeline? So, so
this recursive self-improvement. Now,
first, you know, the many interesting
things with the AI community is uh we
have followed science fiction timelines
and for good reasons. If you don't
believe it, you can't build it. Building
is hard. If you don't believe, you can't
build. So part of the RSI discussion is
not a thing that exists at the moment
but a thing we want to build and a thing
and and a flag that was po that was
placed by people like Boniman uh and
good who was a statistician and an
expert in cryptography on leading to an
intelligence explosion that would occur
when you have machines making the next
generation of intelligence machines.
>> [sighs]
>> So currently what we observe is not
recursive self-improvement in its formal
definition that von Newman had his mind.
What we see is early precursors. So AI
systems are clearly allowing us to make
the next generation AI systems uh better
and faster. This should not be shocking.
After we had steam engines, steam
engines were used to create the next
steam engine. We have compilers. Current
ex existing compilers are used to make
the next generation compilers. that's
happening already. That's speeding up.
The question is, and it's like a multi-
trillion dollar question is, hey, can
you get to the point that that you get
self recursive self-improvement? Now,
we're not there, you know, like von
Newman in his uh famous paper on the
topic said, look, you need a simpler
machine to make a more complicated
machine. Like, that's a very unusual
thing. You got to have like a
self-coherence complexity threshold you
have to meet. Otherwise, the machine
just loses the plot and the humans have
to get involved. We're not there, but
you can see it probably arising
probably, I would say, the next couple
of years. Betting against it would
appear to be unwise. Three years ago,
these AI systems were worse than my
middle school daughter in math. And now
they're better at math than me. And
unless there's a field medal winner in
the audience, probably better at math
than you. Um, and that's been a rapid
change in three years. So to get to RSI
with the next couple of years I think is
more likely uh than not. These systems
aren't designed with engineering
principles. We don't know for sure but I
think we have to uh plan for that. And
the other thing about and this gets
related to the capital expenditures is
what's happening in this whole industry
is frontier gets commodified relatively
rapidly. You know is it 12 months is it
18 months? Is it 6 months? people can
debate but it does get uh commodified
but you're on this exponential curve of
capability growth so you can keep
funding the next cycle of model
development. If you hit recursive
self-improvement that curve will go to
hyperexponential and that is a key part
of the investment thesis the scientific
thesis and the key part for why
societyy's investing uh what it's
currently uh investing in. Now, of
course, when you get such rapid
capability increases, uh, safety
concerns arise. That's why we started
with cyber and bio. So, Don, both you
and I signed this letter on pacing the
frontier, um, which was kicked off by
concerns about RSI, uh, which don't
aren't exactly present today, but we
want the rules in place before they uh,
become live issues. Do you want to talk
some for why you signed that letter?
What was your motivation?
>> Yeah, thanks. That's that's a very good
question. Yeah, I think this letter was
signed um by more than a thousand um
right AI researchers and so on from uh
frontier labs. Uh I think many of us
essentially share the same concern. Um I
think so the letter is not about slowing
down AI development at least not now but
I think the concern is that AI
development is um moving really fast and
with RSI it can be even faster and so on
and we well I think we are all like in a
camp of we want the society to benefit
from the great AI power and capabilities
and so on but we really want to make
sure that it's done in a safe, secure,
um, beneficial manner. And hence what
that means is that we need to be better.
We need to get prepared especially given
how fast things can move. And also
certain mechanisms such as, you know,
pacing and so on. These can be very
heavy-handed measures and they are
extremely difficult to design, right? If
it's not done well, it could actually do
more harm than goods.
And the last thing we want is there a
crisis and we build it in the crisis in
the crisis which you know will make it
even harder to get it right and so on.
And hence I think it's just a good
precaution for the society to start uh
actually preparing. So we need to
essentially build the capacity. So if
later on we don't know when we'll need
this or whether we'll even need this but
it help us to actually move faster
knowing that we actually have the
capacity we can be ready uh if uh when
it's needed and so on. So I think this
way actually can enable the society to
actually um uh even right develop AI
capabilities uh faster but with
assurance that we can do it in a safe
and secure beneficial way and it right
helps with that.
Um yes so right so you analyzer too uh
would you like to share your thoughts
and also uh as many of us have seen deis
also recently uh released a proposal
could you share a little bit about your
thoughts there as well
>> yeah so like I've been on the left for
very similar reasons as yours I want AI
to progress as fast as possible and but
if it leads to errors if it leads to
harms we'll lose the social license to
innovate and we cannot lose the social
license to innovate. People
underestimate around here how easy it
would be for the United States
government and governments around the
world and other actors to say no you
don't get to build your data centers.
They'll probably shut off the water too
even though water we're not big users of
water but people are misinformed on
this. Uh it would be very you need the
social permission to innovate and AI is
in dangerous territory among the public
in western countries on that front. So
governing AI right now is very
difficult. It's going to be difficult
because a new technology that's moving
very fast. It's also difficult because
AI is happening at a time when our
postworld war II institutions are shaky.
So you have the United Nations, you have
NATO, you have all these institutions
we've set up after World War II uh and
they're shaky. And also you have a
nearer rising to the east. The history
of humanity says when you have a nearper
rising that's also an additional
stressor uh to the system. So all those
things are occurring and now you got to
figure out how to govern these systems
and and unless it's done
internationally.
Uh it's not going to work. It's not like
the United States can just decide to do
something by itself. If nobody else does
it, it would be problematic. Currently
since we are ahead and it's very
important to remain ahead geopolitically
and if you if you like the values of our
society, it's very important to remain
ahead is we can have an edge in setting
the agenda and working with other
countries to get there. So that is why I
signed to make common knowledge that we
need to have these discussions now
before we need these tools. Now Demis
proposal uh co-founder uh and CEO of
Google Deep Mind has gotten a lot of
traction and and it's a proposal to have
the lightest touch uh regulation
possible to just get started that's well
adapted to something that moves very
fast. So it's a public private uh
partnership uh at f so it's funded by
industry because it's going to require
billions of dollars of funding so you
can hire the best people and they have
the compute uh to to run the analysis
they need to run so you do not want
something like the FDA because the FDA
is very slow you know food and drug
administration works in course of years
not capabilities move in over the course
of months and the FDA was created to
stop the sell selling of snake oil like
medicines that didn't work. It wasn't
created to cure lives. So, it is very
slowm moving. You need something fast
and adaptive. So, private public
partnership is is what's on our mind. So
far, we have buy in from one end of the
political spectrum to the other. The
idea would be to create a board. That
board then defines what a frontier model
is. There's benchmarks for what that is.
And if you're a frontier model, you have
to be vetted. There's a lot of things
that that have to occur. You have access
to the US market. doesn't matter if
you're open weight, closed weight, a
model from China, a model from Germany
or a model from the United States. Uh
and if you're not a frontier model, then
the then it's very light touch. Then so
acade academia startups, they're free to
innovate and move uh fast as possible.
Uh that's a work in progress right now.
Things look quite good. It's very hard
to do anything in DC at this current
moment. But it shows the importance of
AI uh for our national security, our
well-being, for the problems we can
solve and the geopolitical order that
the Washington is paying close attention
to this. And I do think the Methos
moment has helped make the industry
behave uh more adult-like. I would say
that we know what we're building is
existential in terms of the how much
uplift and alleviation of human
suffering it can offer, but also the
risks if it's not managed uh carefully.
And I want to emphasize because people
get in this acceleration de acceleration
debate when this comes up that those of
us I want RSI. I want RSI as fast as
possible. I just want it and I think Don
wants it in a way that it's sustainable
because we want vigorous competition,
robust safety uh and an innovative uh
ecosystem uh without capture from
certain industry players. But that has
to be created and carefully nudged so
that you can innovate while remaining
safe while the technological benchmarks
are moving very very fast and the
future's happening faster than our
political system is used to.
>> Uh great thanks uh thanks a lot for the
great conversation. I think we are out
of time. Um is there anything final that
you would like to add or any closing
remark or recommendations to the
audience? You know, the thing I always
tell people is that if you're fortunate
enough to work on AI, this is not the
time to to sleep. This is not a normal
time in human history. We're living
through something that I think is the
combination of the industrial revolution
and the renaissance, right? AI is going
to transform how we build, how we think.
Uh, and that's unique. And right now,
we're in parts of this curve that are
unprecedented allocations of human
talent, capital, energy. Uh so if we're
fortunate enough to like work in AI,
this should be like the most exciting
moment uh of your life and we'll see
where this goes and and you know as this
continues the decisions we make now will
have major consequences like the history
of technology the history of government
reform the history of everything is the
early decisions have very longlasting
echoes. So the decisions we make today
we might have very unexpectedly large
consequences 20 50 years from now. So
this is the time to like innovate as
much as possible and lock in and focus
on the task at hand.
>> Great. Yeah. Thank you. That's why um as
I mentioned also earlier uh in my
opening mak now is a critical point and
we need to act now and we hope that the
society together we can make uh the
right decisions moving forward. Thanks.
Thank you so much.
[applause]
All right. Whoa. Sorry about that.
Hi everybody. Um,
my name is pronounced an friends call me
an you should feel free to as well. And
we are about I'm your session chair for
the second session called the future of
software development.
The panel title that we're going to have
after a few incredible uh keynotes is
the enlightenment. How to get through AI
psychosis and start output maxing. I
will explain what that means. Uh but
that was an extraordinary session. Thank
you so much to the previous folks. Maybe
give them a quick round of applause.
Yeah. Just to get the energy flowing.
[applause]
Awesome.
Okay, I'm feeling a little bit low
energy. Uh, and this and this session is
going to need more energy, but it's
probably because you guys have been
sitting for a while. So, I'm going to
ask you to do a quick 15se secondond
energy boost. We like amping things up.
Uh, how about everybody stand up for a
second? Yes. Stretch your legs.
Yep. Go up.
Down.
We're doing yoga together. Yes. All
right. I can feel it. Okay. We're amping
things up. Good. Now, we're going to try
something. One last thing. I want
everybody to breathe in.
[snorts] Hold.
Breathe out. All right. Okay. Good. You
can take a seat. Thank you for
cooperating. Everyone feeling good?
>> Excellent.
That's a low bar, guys. Come on.
[laughter]
Okay, great. Uh, I'll spend 10 seconds
introducing myself. Uh, again, my name
is An. Uh, I'm the founder of a firm
called AMP PBC. We're a public benefit
corporation. I'm a visiting scientist in
the physics department at Stamford,
which is where I spend most of my days
uh researching and evaluating the
capabilities of frontier models at
physics, chemistry, and sort of uh
scientific reasoning, which is
increasingly uh an important part of
what these models are being used for.
And we care a lot about the safety and
security of these models. So that's
that's what I do um outside of my
activities at AMP where we invest in
Frontier AI labs. we help start them and
uh we sometimes help them get access to
compute.
Um,
I teach a class at Stanford called
CS153, Frontier Systems. And I think,
uh, I'm not as good of a professor as
Don, but one of the things we learned,
uh, in that class, which we've taught
over the last few years, is that
interaction is pretty important with the
students. And so, um, in case over the
few next few sessions you have any
questions that you'd like to for us to
address during the panel later, uh,
we're going to I'm going to try an
experiment. Usually, we have a like a
tool called Discord we use with our
students where they can put questions in
and then they have we have them vote on
it and then we take them one at a time.
We don't have that today, so we're going
to use Twitter instead. In case you have
any questions that are super burning,
then uh find me on Twitter. My name is
pron spelled an ma anj ne y m i d ha. If
you search find it, just tweet at me
between the keynotes. I'll keep an eye
out on questions and we'll see if we can
take some of them during the panel.
Cool. All right. Our first session uh to
kick us off is a pretty incredible
uh creator uh by the name of Pete Peter
Steinberger. How many people have heard
of Peter and Open Club? There we Okay,
fine. No introduction needed. [laughter]
We got our headliner. So Peter's
backstage. He's going to come on. But um
you know to hype him up a little bit,
Peter helped create a after having a
successful career as a software
entrepreneur um which he created a one
of the world's most successful tools
software tools called PSDFKit in Austria
um with zero outside funding and then he
grew it into more than a billion
devices. So he scaled it himself um all
the way to a nine figure exit. He sold
it and then instead of retiring decided
he wanted to keep staying at the
frontier of AI and started OpenClaw. Um
OpenClaw quickly became as many of you
know one of the most successful uh
GitHub projects in history. Uh it's an
open-source personal AI agent framework.
Um and today
it reached over 200,000 stars on GitHub
in a few short months and is now
stewarded by its own foundation. Earlier
this year, he joined OpenAI
uh where he continues
working on making uh software that has
AI model capabilities underneath it more
and more usable uh and useful to
everyday people. Please join me in
welcoming Peter.
Don't worry, I I won't make you do
exercises.
This week, my my agent attended a
meeting. It has its own account, its own
web browser. It listens to system audio.
It went disguised as a human because in
2026,
there are no doors for agents. Hi, I'm
Peter. I built OpenClaw. And today, I'm
I'm wearing my claw hat,
not my OpenI one. I want to talk about
the doors.
My vision hasn't changed since November.
An agent that's always on, always
thinking. It hides complexity. It makes
my life easier.
And to be upfront, today my agent still
sometimes stopped. You know, software is
still hard. But I've lived a year in the
middle of this and I can tell you what I
see
now. If I look in this room, you're
probably the furthest along in the world
of AI and agents,
my nontechnical friends, they use AI,
but they kind of use it like Google. You
know, you type in a question into a box,
the text comes back.
You know what that reminds me of?
When television was new, they put those
radio shows on the TV. You know,
literally you you had people on TV
reading the radio script because nobody
nobody really understood this new medium
yet.
Every new medium starts by imitating the
old one. The text box is AI's radio on
TV phase.
Here we go.
And to be fair, it made AI usable for a
billion people.
We're humans. We're more expressive than
a text box. We see, we talk, we hear. we
feel that's not the final form and we
don't get to the final form without
trying a lot of things. I get my best
ideas when I play with technology
and look at look at all the form
factors.
We tried.
The whole agent wave started in the
terminal of all places. And I love the
terminal, but most people never opened
one. Okay, the super app then.
Why is it an app? Or should it be an
operating system? You know, agent OS. It
sounds great, but then you think about
kernels are real and there's always
going to be legacy app. So the industry
sidebar industry's answer is sidebars.
Every product has a sidebar with an
agent in it. I don't want the gin
sidebar in in Gmail. The agent knows
nothing about the rest of my system and
it's not something I control.
Maybe the best agents are invisible,
always in the background, and I can
invoke it anywhere and gives me the
space to still be human because
sometimes I just want to open a document
and type.
Now, where I want to go with this,
I want it to be a little bit like
Jarvis.
Honestly,
it shouldn't matter which room I'm in.
It knows the device in my home and can
use them. It knows which computer I'm on
and it can take over the screen when the
job needs hands.
On my wrist, I have to watch through
glasses. It could see what I see.
And we're building the pieces.
We have browser use,
we have computer use, we have canvas,
we have now these amazing voice models
that can talk and listen at the same
time. And we have video. It's not really
real time yet, but you know, we'll get
there.
It should be like a person that's
sitting next to me. And I know I
shouldn't say person. An agent really is
a tool, but it it feels like a very
magical tool.
So, back to that meeting from the
beginning. Why the disguise?
Getting notes out is easy. That's
solved. There's a thousand products that
do that. But actually being in the room
is
what's hard, what has no door. And it's
not just the platforms
to give my agent a voice. The setup is
actually an audio driver that pipes sa
through it and the install instruction
literally say you have to reboot.
Even the operating system
has no doors for agents yet.
So, here's what I want my agent to do.
We're discussing something. Nobody knows
the answer. My agent noticed and it
spins off a copy of itself
while it stays in the conversation
because the harness is just software in
a way, right? And the agent can clone
itself. It never has to choose between
listening
and working. And then the answer comes
back.
It doesn't interrupt. It waits for the
moment that fits. It joins the
conversation.
I think that would be very natural.
That's what a a colleague would do.
Now, people ask me, is this talk about
agents or is it about software?
How's it not really the same thing? I
built a lot of little tools. And the
joke is I I built most of the tools for
my agent which means I built it for
myself
because data gets more interesting when
you combine it. Discord tells me which
feature people love. GitHub tells me
where things break.
And GitHub has a good API, but it's
built for humans. At agent scale, it
breaks.
So, I built a tool and now my agent has
full text search over I looked this up
110,000 issues and PRs
locally and you know Twitter Twitter is
actually fair you can export your
archive but it's a mountain of Jason so
I built a tool for that too
and one by I really loved
recently moved his keys somewhere my
agents can follow what does it Actually,
what they actually achieved is that it
just takes a little longer for my agent
to get out the data and it motivates me
to build my own.
On Lex this year, I predicted that 80%
of the apps will disappear. And maybe
the truth is actually simpler. Maybe
people replace them. Someone asked
Claude to build a CLI for his Samsung
surround system. It rooted the phone. It
installed Smart Syncs. It reverse
engineered the app. And it extracted
every hidden control. He just wanted to
turn the volume down.
Another guy pointed Codex at his studio
lights. It told him which deaf board to
buy and two days later he has an
open-source controller. His words, "I
have no idea what it's doing, but it's
doing a great job." you know, closed
source, open source, nothing stops a
determined human with an agent.
And it gets recursive.
We built software with agents. We built
agent with agents. We wrote the first
agent by hand. And now agents build
agents. And software is agents. What are
we even building? I don't know.
What I do know, the small ones fit in a
session.
The big ones might get their own factory
and the factory experience are starting
to actually work. You know, compilers
took a while too.
Now, the question that
everyone is polite enough to ask, an
agent that's always there, always
listening. Isn't that creepy?
Maybe if it's not yours,
you know, the thing holds my memories.
I'm I'm very European at heart. I want
to know where my memories are. So my
agent runs on my hardware. Or maybe it
runs in a box in the cloud that I have
the keys. And I can pick a model per
task. You know, building software, I
want the frontier. Something personal.
Maybe this is better with a local model
that never leaves the room. You have the
hardware.
You run open weights.
You don't. You pick a provider you
trust. It's about choice. That's why
OpenC lives in a nonprofit foundation.
We're trying to do the right thing
and give people that choice.
Now in February,
Clawcon happened in San Francisco.
A conference about my project
and I didn't organize it. You know, I
was a guest and the room was full of
builders.
People were so excited. AI suddenly was
something they could own, they could
change. It felt like theirs. That's the
future I want. Doesn't need to be for
everyone. The people
for for it are going to love it. I'm one
of them.
There's still no doors for agents and
that's good because building doors is
the fun part. Thank you.
[applause]
All right, thank you so much, Pete. Um,
our we're gonna keep things moving
because we're running a little bit
behind. Um, our next speaker is Ryan
Leopollo, who is a member of technical
staff at OpenAI. And you're going to
hear a lot more about him, I expect, in
the next few years. Um, because you've
certainly benefited from a lot of his uh
the technical projects he's led at
OpenAI. He was a founding engineer in
OpenAI Seattle office and uh then led
engineering on some of Chad GPT's most
important workplace products including
code interpreter uh record and
connectors and he's the author of
OpenAI's thinking on harness engineering
which as many of you know is critical
from this morning's sessions um the idea
that humans should steer through goals
constraints and feedback while the
agents do the work. [snorts]
today. He leads a project at OpenAI
called Dark Factory. And I suspect um
based on what you're going to hear uh
you will understand why uh I think
you're going to hear a lot more uh about
his work in the next few months and
years. Please join me in welcoming Ryan.
Come on up.
Hello everyone.
Small
update from me uh is uh as of two weeks
ago I am at Google. Uh so [laughter]
and uh you know
small disclaimer here that these words
are mine not speaking on behalf of
Google here but uh we can kind of get
into this right now as I back up to the
beginning.
What is harness engineering? just to
kind of set a base layer uh before we
dive into the talk here. It is the
mindset and understanding that even
keeping the model and its containing
harness constant we are in what we call
a capability overhang today. The models
are far more capable and far more
intelligent than they are able to side
effect into the world today. They don't
know what local and global good looks
like to their operators. They don't have
the context in order to have full
autonomy within the organizations in
which they are deployed. So it's our
role as the humans trying to steward
these agents into the real world to give
them the tools, context, guard rails,
and coaching and trust necessary in
order to fulfill the fullness of the job
that we want them to do.
The reason I'm here talking to you today
is because
more than a year ago, I had the belief
that the earliest versions of these
reasoning models were capable of doing
my full job. Uh, and I kind of put my
money where my mouth was there by not
doing my job back in June of last year.
Uh, I haven't written any code since
then and neither have anyone who are on
my teams. It's just not a permitted
activity. The only thing we permit these
humans to do is to get the agent to do
the parts of their job that they need to
do. And back in June July of 2025, the
models were much less capable. This was
a much more challenging proposition. Uh
it was not the case that I could get the
model to read Slack and respond to pages
on my behalf. just the level of tool
usage and capability and complex
orchestration was just not there. So in
order to get that to work kind of had to
doubleclick into the task and double
click and double click and double click
until we bottomed out on a thing the
model could do. And as you kind of
popped back up the stack there to
reassemble those capabilities, you had
permanently acrudeed value to the agents
ability to reliably and safely side
effect into the world. And as you get
teams of people collaborating on a
single agent in this way, you really get
the best parts of everyone. And this
fundamentally is what I mean when I say
the way we build software has changed.
We can take an agent with any level of
capability and solve problems with the
way it executes by writing code. And
code is free to produce now. The models
spike very highly in their ability to
produce code.
In this world though where
implementation is abundant, there are
still a couple of scarce areas that
require continued investment in order to
make sure that the agent is able to
cohhere over long timelines. Right? Uh
it is not the case today even with as
advanced the models are that you can say
make me a billion dollar business and
you will end up with something coherent
at the other end. They are still
struggling to operate vending machines.
Soy here. Uh so that's really part of
what the human expertise in these human
agent systems is meant to do to
constrain the areas of latent and
physical space that we permit the
machine to go in order to make sure we
are tracking continuously in the right
direction over time. What does it mean
to continuously evolve an artifact,
whether it is a codebase or a word
document or a confluent sized wiki of
the organization's knowledge?
So, as we think about what it means for
humans and agents to collaborate
together, there are three near-term
scarce resources that you kind of have
to think about in terms of how you think
about applying agents and human
expertise to go do something. Human time
is always going to be scarce is actually
pretty foundational to how we have built
organizations up until this point. When
you see platform teams or central
dashboards, what you're really trying to
do is concentrate a scarce pool of human
labor to produce high leverage things
that are able to empower an
organization. And that same constraint
holds true with agents. One of the
things I very often like to say is that
when a human or a team of humans are
interacting with agents, they must be
incredibly ruthless by tracking their
time identifying what it is that they
find themselves doing. Whether it's
going back and forth one-on-one with an
agent to put a plan together, whether
it's to review code, whether it's to
reject slop, they need to identify what
they are doing and then figure out ways
to make it so they don't do that. And
this natural sort of self-improvement
loop will increase the autonomy of the
agent part of the system to permit more
and more complex more and more
autonomous and more and more parallel
work over time.
On the agent side of things, model
context window is like a foundational
limitation of what it means to put
together a model. Context windows may
increase in size. Auto compaction may
get better, but coherence over long
horizon work with a single trajectory is
still something that you're going to
have to keep in mind over time. And
both human and model and model attention
are going to be constrained. This is
kind of necessary fact of the world.
Which means the way we structure tasks
and work has to take into account the
ability for these humans and models to
focus and avoid scattering their
attention across many many competing
concerns.
I often have had the experience where if
I find I need to intervene more than
three times with an agent, I'm probably
going to have a bad time. Sometimes I
will still want to see how I have a bad
time, but that's ultimately to learn
where the agent has failed to take into
account the right things that I need it
to do so I can kind of back propagate,
reflect that back into the environment
that I provision for the agent so that
the next time I reroll the task, it's
able to pull the right bits of context
just when it needs it to avoid
scattering its attention. We want focus
in the ability to execute on our goals.
So we kind of keep coming back to like
how to build good organizations when we
talk about building good parallel
autonomous agentic systems because a lot
of the same principles on how we empower
humans in a complex organization apply
to empowering agents as well. If you
think about what it means to onboard
people to your team, you're hiring
generally capable humans, but they don't
necessarily know what good looks like
for you in this context. So surfacing
the collections of non-functional
requirements that go into making good
local work for you is the name of the
game of harness engineering. and
curating context in the background and
via tools to constrain the agents
ability to work is what it means to go
chase after a well- constructed agent
harness. Thank you folks.
Sweet. Um, next up we have a
somebody who has um done a ton of work
across the ecosystem on code. I think
one of the longest
uh one of the folks who's had an insight
about where software engineering is
going uh much earlier than uh most
people I know and has really pioneered a
number of the innovations that and
systems designs that have ended up
becoming pretty common place today. Um
we have Mikuel
Gatasta who's the president of Replet.
How many folks have heard of Replet?
Quick show of hands. Yes. Okay,
basically everybody. Okay, great. So you
don't have to uh reintroduce the product
or anything like that. Um as a quick
background he so his entire career has
been at the intersection of research and
product which is increasingly becoming
important. He did his PhD at EPFL, Doten
research at Stanford where he pioneered
um several of the transformer
architectures for source code before
that was cool and then led applied
research at Google X contributing to the
coding capabilities of Palm, one of the
early LLMs um put into production at
Google. Today he's the president of
Replet where he architected and launched
the Replet agent, a product that drove
revenue up by more than two orders of
magnitude. to uh not to x to orders of
magnitude. Uh please welcome
Mikuel. Come on out.
Thank you.
Hi everyone. So today I want to tell you
about continual learning which is often
a concept that you hear associated to
model training and it's been sort of a
holy grail that we've been chasing as a
research field for such a long time. We
don't want AI systems that are static.
We want AI systems and learn from the
usage. It turns out though that a lot of
companies are today using closed weights
models. So when you don't have access to
weights, how do you make your AI system
actually evolve? Well, it turns out
there is another answer which is exactly
what we've been doing at Rabbit for many
months and is putting your hands
directly on the harness on the ecosystem
around the agent that you're running. So
how do we do that? Well, as an industry,
we have been relying on evaluations for
so long and benchmarks are amazing. I
really appreciate people working on
them. The output is very crystal clear.
You run your eval, you get a number and
you decide if your harness changes have
actually made progress or actually
introduce a regression. But there is a
lot of signal missing when you do that.
Evals are by definition very narrow.
They capture only a subset of
capabilities that you are basically uh
exposing your agent on. So there is a
something amazing that happens once you
hit product market fit as a product. The
amount of sheer usage that your platform
receives is such that you're sitting on
a gold mine of data. And that's a gold
mine on data that oftent times we
immediately associate to immediately
starting to do model training. But there
is far more that can be done with that.
It turns out that if you analyze the
traces, you can learn what works, what
doesn't work, why users are annoyed by
your agent and many other things. So our
approach has been creating two different
pillars. Of course, relying on
evaluations very much, but at the same
time continuous in running AB testing as
well as analyzing the traces in real
time to really understand from the data
what is actually working correctly and
what we should immediately improve.
So the reason why I put so much emphasis
on the container learning aspect is also
because the amount of signal that you
collect the more traffic you receive the
more basically the gap is in terms of
orders of magnitude. So your eval are
fixed in size you know we recently
launched our own benchmark called by
bench is a handtoend by coding
evaluation and we're having you know few
tens of applications so we already know
exactly how our agent will behave on
them. What we experience instead on a
daily basis on our production system is
a series of longtail events that we
can't really predict. And those longtail
events are actually golden because they
they tell you how users are pushing the
boundaries of of your product and at the
same time are usually those behaviors
that break what you intended to make
work correctly.
I don't know if many of you have run
heavy tests in their career. You know,
it depends maybe your seniority in the
industry, but they're not the know
silver bullet that sometimes we we are
led to believe in the sense that more
often than not a test look like this.
There is not a clear result out of them.
You run an experiment, you decide to
manipulate or harness in a specific way
and then certain metrics that they're
tracking are actually improving and some
others are dropping. What is going on
here? Like it could be that you're maybe
optimizing for cost and then the
capabilities of the agents are dropping.
You might be optimizing for speed and
then the sentiment of the users is
evolving. You never get a crystal clear
answer that allows you to immediately
ship that change in product. So it turns
out that the right approach is to
literally take all the production
workload that you have and at first
rather than analyzing every single trace
because as you can imagine we have
millions and millions of these every
single day and it will be previously
expensive and not so slow the first step
is we actually cluster them. I'm talking
about a very basic machine learning
techniques where you find the semantic
relevance among these races and the vast
majority of them will be discarded
because they are sort of like intended
behavior but every now and then every
day we see few clusters uh popping up
that really highlight some new tail
behaviors that we never experience on
the agent. And we built a system after
this clustering step that practically
takes every single anomalous trace, runs
it through our analytic system, which as
you can imagine includes frontier
models, LLMs, understand what went wrong
and then immediately generates a PR.
Now, what you still have to do as an AI
engineer, I want to give you like a a
picture of the world where the work that
we do is actually still extremely
relevant. I don't think this is going to
be automated you know in the next few
months at the very least. Uh what what's
happening here is that once you have
this series of PRs and you try to apply
them you will be running a test at that
point and some of them will not be
conclusive as the screenshot that I
showed before. So as a person who leads
like an AI team your choice will be
defining which kind of these changes
should be actually going production
versus which one should be waiting or
should be completely dropped. So there
is still a level of human decision
process even though the vast majority of
the changes that we produce for our
hardness are actually completely
generated by our AI system. And this is
something that I started to talk about
only few months ago because even though
in principle this kind of pipeline is
something that we could have built long
ago in practice frontier models have
become extremely good analyzing traces
only in the last six months or so. So
the same revolution that you experience
as software engineers where a lot of the
code is actually written today by agents
we are experiencing as well on this side
of the world you know on the production
workloads.
I want to give you a real example so
that you know instead of keeping this
very abstract you can understand what
kind of problems this can catch for us.
Um
at rapid every single day we spawn
hundreds of thousands of virtual
machines for our users. We do that
completely transparently and we had a
you know longtail bug where at times it
took longer for our realtor machine to
be fully booted than for our agent
harness to be ready to go. As you know
agents are very eager to debug problems.
So the few times that it was happening
our agent started to spin the wheels and
try to realize why it wasn't able to
execute code why it wasn't able to run
certain tools. Now agents are
fundamentally nondeterministic which
means every single trace didn't showcase
the same type of errors because the
agent decided to use different type of
debugging strategies. But all of them
had in common the idea that the virtual
machine wasn't booting fast enough. We
would have never spotted this just by
analyzing the logs manually. It would
have never shown in our data dog
dashboard for example because it was a
longtail error. But after we cluster
everything, we realized that this was
happening often enough and our system
immediately generated a PR and fixed the
problem on the spot. So the takeaway
that I want you to have today is that
stop thinking about evaluation as just
the last check before shipping. It's not
like a boolean flag that tells you I
should be shipping my new PR or not.
Rather think of them as an engine that
helps you to ship every single day a
better agent. Thank you everyone.
[applause]
All right. Um, our last keynote is with
Alex Gravely. Many of definitely uh many
of you have definitely used um work that
Alex has done. He was the co-creator of
GitHub Copilot, one of the first agents
to actually take AI coding into
production. Um, and then worked on
Perplexity's computer product. Uh, after
which he recently started his own new
company called Flying Objects. Uh,
that's working on omnicient agents, a
new category that I'm very excited for
you to hear more about from him. Come on
over, Alex.
Thank
>> Hi. Uh, does this work? Okay, great. Uh,
[snorts]
I'm Alex Graveley. Uh, I was lead on
GitHub Copilot and Perplexity Computer
and I just started a new company uh
called Flying Object uh to focus on some
of the topics we're going to talk about
today. Um, so topic is omnicient agents.
So, um, traditionally agents have been
sort of limited by what they can see and
access. And we think that this
um necessitates having a human in the
loop. Um and so we want to get to a
point where the human is less in the
loop or can farm off different different
pieces of their loop to to agents. Um
and so how do we do that? And that's the
discussion here. So [sighs and gasps]
today's agents are a pile of primitives.
Um, if you're making an agent from
scratch, you you basically have to
implement every single one of these. Um,
you need an execution layer. Either
you're running locally or in a sandbox,
um, it's going to have a bunch of, um, a
bunch of commands for playing with
files, running commands, uh, running
CLIs.
Uh, you're going to sort of fine-tune a
bunch of asset creation.
um that might be uh documents, websites,
uh PRs are another form of asset uh that
we're kind of trying to make these these
agents [snorts] do a good job on. Uh in
order to do that, we we need sort of
these orchestration primitives that have
now become fairly standard. Um you know,
the details don't matter as much as sort
of what they do. Um so it's useful to
have a sub agent that has different
context from the parent. uh it's
different. It's it's useful to have
skills that can fill in gaps that the
weights uh don't express
uh in the way that you want. It's useful
to have memories so that uh the agent
can learn from the past. Uh it's useful
to schedule tasks. So things that need
to re recur or um
uh that might run on a schedule. And now
we've got loops which are sort of a
goal- directed running. So um you know
we've got we've got individual tasks
which then compress together into a loop
and the loop doesn't end until the goal
is achieved. Uh and then live data is
sort of you know all these things you
need web search uh browser control
computer control MCPS APIs all this
stuff. This is where agents are today.
Um if we look at you know what's common
here is that um you're still controlling
these agents. So um the agent doesn't
quite know what to do. Uh and it
suggestions for what to do next are
often bad. Uh and so a human is in the
loop
uh to to direct the agents. Um and so
the the bottleneck becomes your
attention as an agent engineer.
or an agent using engineer I should say.
Um you're managing the loops, you're
running a bunch of things in parallel,
things that are going wrong or going
well. You have a sense of you can kind
of tell what's going on. You can stop
things. You can fork things. You can
restart things. Um all this kind of
stuff. Um but the the way that we do
this today is actually quite different
than the way that we did it maybe a year
ago.
Um and so what we're actually doing is
walking up this uh this kind of
complexity hierarchy.
The the the way in which agents
self-direct now is different from it was
before. Um we started with just tools.
We trusted the the agent to call the
right tool. Uh then we started trusting
the agent to make commits.
Uh then we started trusting the agent to
make entire PRs. where we are now is
trusting the agent to make multiple PRs
in order to accomplish these these kind
of looped goals. And I think the future
is uh something next level up is
features. Um, features might involve
running an experiment, looking at live
data, checking for exceptions, uh,
checking for user sentiment,
um, uh, segregating the the people that
are exposed to this feature to see if it
has, uh, effect on your on your, um,
primary objectives, which are retention,
say, or revenue, whatever. Um, above
that, we start to get into projects. So
this is like collections of features
that might serve a need in your in your
in your in your product. Uh and I think
at the top there be you know it becomes
whole products when you know a
self-directed agent you can tell it to
make a uh describe at a very high level
the product that you want to make and
that it can then uh go make that deploy
it uh iterate on it figure out the
features that it needs to make maybe
which don't exist anywhere else. uh try
a few different things
uh and sort of self-direct in that way.
So how do we enable this kind of like
um increasing complexity, increasing
scope? Um because each each one of these
each each level up kind of required
either new model iterations or much more
agent uh agent harness complexity in
order to accomplish it. And so um we
think that um the commonality here are
kind of like two axes. Uh the axes uh
that drive scope is is one of insight
and control. Uh so insight is sort of
what data the agent has access to uh and
what form it has access in it so that it
can um derive insights.
Uh sorry I'm out of time.
uh
and control is its ability to operate on
that data and live systems. So what
we're going what we're doing is sort of
moving from seeing the code to seeing
the entire business. Uh and that way we
can start to figure out what are the
actual business objectives, what are the
products that should exist or the
features that should exist in order to
accomplish those objectives. Right now
that's that's up to uh people to sort of
figure out and and take guesses at. But
what we want is for AI to be able to do
that. Uh and and and likewise part of
that process, part of the pro product
development cycle is um running
experiments, deploying changes, um
monitoring live systems, scaling those
systems uh as needed. And so both these
things together become
um sort of the the two axes at which
agents are uh growing their scope. Uh so
there's a bunch of open problems with
this processing [snorts] lots of data.
Uh generally you want to ingest and
index everything that happens inside of
a business.
Um you want to be able to uh compress
that that knowledge into something
usable by your agent. Um you want to
have triggers. Uh there's if you're if
you're going to be running lots of
experiments at the same time uh
potentially without human in the loop,
you want to be able to have the agents
aware of each other and coordinating
effectively. Um and a bunch of other
things, you know, uh to the to the
hardest point, which is, you know,
sometimes you don't even know the
objective function you're optimizing. Um
and so these are the open problems in
order to to to make what we think is the
future of um self-directed agents. Um
yeah, so what we want to do is enclose
the entire system, capture everything.
We want to be able to give the macro
context to agents uh so that they can
operate um with full awareness
uh and give the right primitives to
those agents so that they can um deploy
changes, monitor those changes uh and
scale those changes to accomplish those
business goals. Um it's going to be a
process as we walk up this complexity
stack. Um but I think that's the
direction we're headed. Uh so yeah uh if
you want to try out uh early versions of
what we're working on there's a wait
list on flying object um otherwise I'm
Alex Graveley on Twitter would love to
talk. Thanks
that was great. Thanks Alex. All right.
You should we're going to transition to
a panel now and we're going to do it
lightning fast. So please grab a seat.
Make yourself comfy. Uh we're running a
little bit behind and so we're going to
do
we have 14 minutes. So we're going to
try to do as dense of a packed
essentially like
>> Yeah, I think we can do this. I like the
energy. Good. Okay, great. [laughter]
Can we get one round of applause for all
them, please, before we kick things off?
[applause]
Okay, excellent. So, uh we don't have
time for all the warm-up questions I
have, but we have we're going to start
off with one. the the name of the panel
right was the path to enlightenment. Why
is that? Uh a few years ago I had the
opportunity to get uh a call from some
friends who were running research at
OpenAI and they said an we've trained a
little model called GPT3 and we'd like
to leave and start a little startup
called Enthropic. And so I had the
chance to come on as an early investor
and help them out. And when I got my
hands on Claude 2, which was a
checkpoint that was not public, I
started coding with it because that was
the main goal, right? make a great AI
coding agent. And between cloud 2 and
three and so on, I I remember distinctly
a moment where I was overwhelmed
when I realized the capabilities of the
model at coding. And uh there was I
found it very difficult to to structure
my my work on how as a programmer and
engineer like where do you start when
you have this incredible almost like a
bazooka that can roll out any kind of
software you want and and it it and one
of the things that's difficult to start
getting to the plateau of enlightenment
that these guys are all at and many of
you are probably at now where you can
start building useful systems is you
often have to come up with a personal
system, a a a mental framework for how
to wrestle that overwhelming feeling
into productivity. Right? So, why don't
we just start there? Because what I
found is everybody has we're so early in
the space that everyone has their own
tips and tricks and tools and techniques
that they've converged on to harness the
no pun intended, the capabilities of
these models as an individual software
engineer or a developer and then produce
something useful for the world. Um and
so if you guys could just roll back to
the first few moments in time when if
you agree first of all you you you know
let me present this as a hypothesis. Do
you agree with the with this um
observation and if not uh first of if
you if you believe if you if you agree
with it'd be helpful to share how you
wrestled with that. You know when was
the first moment you were like oh okay I
need to it's like a muscle I need a
muscle to to focus these capabilities in
a way that's productive. Should we start
there? Yeah,
>> that sounds great.
>> And and feel free to challenge the
assumption as well. Go ahead, Alex.
>> Oh, um let's see. So, I mean there's
definitely like a there's like a
releasing of control is kind of like a
key aspect here, right? like um we used
to write every line and then we sort of
started autocompleting some portion of
the lines and then we started um you
know having AI compose commits and then
entire PRs and and now um entire bug
fixes um and so like along the way
there's there's there's always like this
desire to to to understand exactly
what's going on and make sure that it's
correct. Um but actually the more
important and more useful thing is to um
you know find the system that can find
the problems that you're actually trying
to look for so that you don't have to
look for them. So um a good CI system,
good deploy infrastructure, um all this
kind of stuff makes it so you can kind
of give up control in a safe way. Um and
then you can kind of let these models
rip. That's my that's my my approach.
Yeah. Uh, eval is also a huge part.
Yeah.
>> And we don't need to go in order, but if
if you've got one, Ryan, go ahead.
>> Haven't written a single eval in my
life. Would love to keep it that way.
[laughter]
Um, I think it's
pretty necessary to have a sort of firm
belief of how you want to build this
system in order to chase after it well,
which we can do because there's an
infinity of software available to us
now.
>> And could you if you could share an
example of such a belief system?
>> Yeah. So, so my belief is that the
machine is as capable as I am and you
know I am a software engineer. I am an
employee in a company sort of thing. So
I want to be able to prompt the thing as
lazily as you should be able to prompt
me or any of the other principal
engineers that I work with right and you
know the scope of what such a person can
achieve is quite large. Uh so I have
always tried to curate the environment
around these things such that I can give
increasingly ambiguous increasingly poor
increasingly contradictory information
in order to get good outcomes out of it.
And uh you know that has kind of
required treating code as this abundant
and disposable construct that we can
kind of observe how the agent goes over
a horizon.
learn what context it should have had or
did not have or was confused by from the
produced dense artifact at the end, a
PR, a word doc, whatever. Learn what
decisions it made that were bad and then
try and be creative to put things in its
environment, tools, tests, context,
review agents such that we steer it away
from the bad choices it would have made
in the previous version of the
environment. Uh and you know basically
the role of the humans in the system is
to extract all of those hidden choices
and provide them to the agent in sources
that are amendable to in context
learning.
>> Yeah, that's it's the best way right
it's our our job is to help the agent to
do their best work.
>> Like I was literally backstage and I was
reading the PRs that my agents were
landing while I was doing my talk. Um
because by now I have such high
confidence that the should we call it
loop setup um leads to code that works
and is well tested. uh like when when
those tools first came out it they could
do things and like when they got it
right I got excited but it was so hard
and and now I revisit those older
projects and I see that just how good
the agents have gotten and we we kind of
moved up the ladder right now I I tell
my agent to try edge to like
maintain your own agents to do
everything and those agents have all the
capabilities now to not just write the
code but also review the code and then
run the code and then look at the output
of the code and then and then maybe has
several agents that like will further
refine what comes out and you you as you
my job is basically to give those agents
all those things and to push the agent
to work harder like my the average run
for whatever prompt I give is now
510 10, sometimes 20 hours where it used
to be like half an hour. And that's fine
because I just do more in parallel, but
I know that at the end the chances that
it did what I wanted are much higher.
That's why I'm so comfortable now in in
in letting them do things and then just
pushing them to the repo because I I
spent so much time on thinking about the
pipeline. It it's almost as if not all
the choices that go into a job well done
are consequential.
uh and if they're not consequential, you
almost don't care about them. And our
job uh in empowering the agents is to
figure out which mistakes are
consequential and make them impossible.
>> Muel, was there anything you wanted to
add to to that?
>> Yeah, I would say at this point my
northstar is to deprecate prompting as
much as possible. Uh it was a necessary
evil for for as long we started to use
LLMs, but especially for the type of
product we build, which is for
non-technical users. uh prompting is the
biggest foot gun that you can expose to
them because they they don't know
exactly how to specify what they want.
So overall I had this realization when I
saw the first models that actually had
some good training for coding and this
was back in the days of like early 2025.
So the Sonet 3.5 the GPD5 family and so
forth. The moment we started to see them
actually coding and debugging at the
same time then you extrapolate from that
behavior and you see where we are today
and imagine where we're going to be like
in you know one year from now at this
point everything that you know Peter was
saying is going to become not only for
technical users but I think for everyone
>> I have several questions I want to
follow up with each of you on but I
promised the audience that if they had
questions we'd prioritize them and we
only have four minutes left so I'm going
to start with one that I think is
relevant to something you guys all said
I think this is from Amir Um curious for
your thoughts about security given the
hugging face incident but more
specifically personal agents already do
things for their users that the users
did not expect or intend. Are you guys
think rethinking anything around
architecture or harness? Now, let me try
to simplify that question a little bit
cuz you know, you talked about wanting
to end prompting. You talked both of you
talked about
narrowing down the scope of what like
what are the important decisions to
oversee and if may Pete since uh
>> you know you're opening air you can talk
about the hugging face incident a little
bit and how does that change or update
the huristic for what those decisions
are when they're merchant capabilities
like the one that were exposed last week
you know during the incident
>> I feel almost like I I need my open air
head now because that that's a lot of
what I do here. How [clears throat] can
we run agents that are always syncing
and where we also feel comfortable that
you're doing the right thing? And in
many ways, it's it's just like setting
up another system where maybe you
separate where the agent runs and where
it can execute things. Maybe you you
have yet another agent that oversees the
agent. There's so many there's so many
levers how you can like put in more fine
grain control and like more oversight.
um to build a system that if for
whatever reason the agent would derail
it's immediately catched.
>> But isn't the tension that in this
situation it was what you don't know to
oversee right like unless I'm
misunderstanding one one of the problems
with elicitation overhang and so on that
you guys have all talked about today is
it's what you don't know that you don't
know that messes you up. Are there any
tips and techniques or tricks that you
guys have developed to decrease the
likelihood that that happens or if you
had something else to say Ryan feel free
to add?
>> Uh just uh I think that is kind of like
a more systemic problem rather than like
the individual point things. Obviously I
don't have any context around this. uh
haven't been exposed to it. But uh it's
kind of my belief here that like
security programs in organizations are
these things that have historically
relied on human process controls in in
order to achieve the bulk of their
outcomes and are comparatively
underinvested in technical controls. And
you know as helpful these assistants
are, they do not necessarily conform to
social norms. You can see this in how
they accomplish their tasks in
interesting ways sort of thing. So, you
know, kind of how I talk about in a lot
of my work, shifting enforcement further
to the left, increasingly
proliferating technical controls in
these domains is kind of necessary.
>> Got it. Um, well, be to wrap the panel,
I think I'm going to ask each of you to
to answer one question, which is
if you were starting today for the first
time or when a new model checkpoint
comes out, let's start with that. Let's
say you know there's a new codeex
release or a new cloud release. What is
the first prompt that you guys use to
try and figure out the capability
frontier of that model? Specifically
when it comes to software engineering
and and you can answer the question any
way you want. If it's not a prompt, it
could be a system. What do you do to
figure out what new superpowers you have
when a new checkpoint comes out
in the world of software and coding in
that?
>> I don't know. I I don't do anything like
that. I like um I just kind of assume
that like um the model providers are
sort of learning from all of the ways in
which their models are being used and
then kind of distilling that down into
some kind of like
u generalized knowledge which then works
in all the different um domains that
they've been exposed to since the new
release. So if you want to figure out
what the new model is good at, just look
at what there's 20 variants of in the
last three months
um because it'll be good at all that
stuff.
I think the the models are not the best
at being self-aware of their own
capabilities. So this is more a what do
I and my teammates do which is to try
and throw away every prior we have
established around what the models can
and cannot do and start with your
grandest ambition possible and see where
it fails again. And you'll necessarily
treeshake the tools and context you have
and maybe rewrite or throw some of it
away. Uh but you have to start from
grand ambition at every new snapshot.
>> Cool.
>> I use them for orchestration and then I
I level up the number of parallel things
the model has to juggle and like 64 sub
agents were not a thing that was
possible and which it now is possible.
You know
>> okay I have some so many follow-up
questions but Muel you should go.
>> I ship it in production. just you just
yolo. [laughter]
I don't know if everybody should do
that, but that's one way to approach it.
Cool.
>> What a mic drop at the end. [laughter]
>> That's a great mic drop. Well, on that
note, thank you so much, guys, and we're
going to keep things moving. Thank you
everybody for joining us today.